<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Epistola ad anglos Being an introduction out of a larger treatise into the mysteries of true Christian religion, by Oliver Hill, exise for the law and the Gospel at Lisbon in Portugal.</title>
            <author>Hill, Oliver, Agent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 124 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 31 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43797</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2004B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218917</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830468</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830468</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34920</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43797)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34920)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2091:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Epistola ad anglos Being an introduction out of a larger treatise into the mysteries of true Christian religion, by Oliver Hill, exise for the law and the Gospel at Lisbon in Portugal.</title>
                  <author>Hill, Oliver, Agent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 58 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for T. B.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the  Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  Evidences, authority, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christianity --  Essence, genius, nature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sin, Original --  History of doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:34920:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>EPISTOLA AD ANGLOS.</hi> BEING AN INTRODUCTION OUT OF A Larger Treatiſe INTO THE MYSTERIES OF TRUE <hi>Chriſtian Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>OLIVER HILL,</hi> Exile for the LAW and the GOSPEL at <hi>Lisbon</hi> in <hi>Portugal.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JEREM. 51.50. ISAI. 62.6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Ye that have eſcaped the Sword do not ſtand ſtill; remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Lord afar off, and let <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> come into your mind: And ye that make mention of the Lord, keep not ſilence.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>T. B.</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:34920:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:34920:2"/>
            <head>EPISTOLA AD ANGLOS. <hi>BEING AN INTRODUCTION OUT OF A Larger Treatiſe INTO THE MYSTERIES OF TRUE</hi> Chriſtian Religion.</head>
            <p>BEcauſe <hi>Adam</hi> fell out of both Pride and Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or deſire of the World; and becauſe all his Children, who bare his <hi>earthly Image, Gen.</hi> 5.3.1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.49. fall after the ſame manner, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.23. <hi>from Chriſt's Heavenly Image, in Love and Humility,</hi> Matth. 11.29. Theſe Two Vices are become the heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary original Sin of Man; whence all Men naturally covet Greatnes and Richeſs as their greateſt Happineſs. So that Greatneſs and Riches being what they moſt covet, and ſet the greateſt value and eſtimation upon, it is no wonder at all if they make them the chief end of their Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and Labours; and therefore regard not the end of the Sciences which they Study and Profeſs, and conſequently neglect (if what Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.24. <hi>That the Man who ſerves two Maſters at once, deſpiſeth one when he waits up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the other,</hi> be true) the means conducing to it. From
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:34920:3"/>whence it comes to paſs that both Maſters and Scholars performing their Exerciſes very perfunctorily, and but <hi>Pro forma</hi> only; not only fall ſhort at firſt of the end of that Science, which they are pretenders to, but alſo by little and little come to forget what are its end and its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per means, and to miſtake thoſe they do make uſe of for the true ones; ſo that by degrees the end and the means became unknown; true Knowledge is loſt at laſt; and new Fancies are ſet up and continue in their room.</p>
            <p>This, as upon a ſerious and due Conſideration it will be found true enough of all real Sciences, ſo it proves but too true of Divinity it ſelf. For I ſay and affirm, That becauſe its Profeſſors apply themſelves to the ſame, out of the Love of Greatneſs and Riches, or Preferment, and ſo regard not its end, and therefore neglect the means requiſite to compaſs it; they know neither what its end (which is the knowledge of God or Salvation) conſiſts in; nor what are the means proper and conducing to that end; and ſo know not Religion or Divinity, which are the known means of the knowledge of God and of Salvation. I ſay here Religion or Divinity, becauſe as the knowledge of God and Salvation is one thing, <hi>The knowledge of God being,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 17.3. <hi>Salvation it ſelf.</hi> So Divinity, which is the means of the ſaid knowledge, and Religion, which is the means of Man's Salvation, being means of but one thing, are but one and the ſame thing, and ſo ſhall be hereafter uſed promiſcuouſly.</p>
            <p>This their Ignorance of what God's Knowledge or Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and of what Divinity or Religion conſiſts in, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears from the words of Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 17.25. who affirms, <hi>That worldly man,</hi> ſuch as theſe are, <hi>know not God:</hi> And from the variety of Opinions which they have at this time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this: For if all the Men that know a thing agree about it, or have but one and the ſame Conceit or Notion
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:34920:3"/>of it, as <hi>Plato</hi> hath ſaid and ſhewed, their different Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Diſſent about theſe Two (Salvation and Religion) is a certain Evidence of their Ignorance of them: Beſides the word Opinion alone implies Ignorance: He that knows, being no more carried away by Conceits and Fancies, or Opinions, but apprehending all things juſt as they are in themſelves, he believes them to be ſo, not becauſe he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives ſo, or hath heard that it is ſo; but becauſe he ſees plainly and underſtands perfectly <hi>per cauſas,</hi> or good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that the things are really ſuch, <hi>John</hi> 4.42. <hi>Prov.</hi> 21.28. Now what Profeſſed Divines have ſuch an underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and knowledge of Salvation, and of Religion as this is, I know not: though many, chiefly amongſt the <hi>Quakers,</hi> have ſo good an Opinion of their Light, and of themſelves, as to be perſwaded that they alone are the people that have engroſſed Wiſdom, or all the Knowledge of God, and of the pure Religion, <hi>Job</hi> 12.2. If they have, let them ſhew it, by making out the hidden Myſteries of God's Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; for both their Faith and Knowledge is to be ſhewed by their Fruits, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.20 <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.18 But if the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture be true, they know not what theſe things are; for the Scripture teacheth us, <hi>That Salvation is to know God, and him whom he hath ſent,</hi> and conſiſteth in Knowledge: and that the means to know God, is to ſear him, by doing his Will, and dying therefore ſo much to our own Will, as to abſtain from all Pride, Covetouſneſs, and Envy, and all other evil Luſts and Deſires of the Fleſh, and as to ſeek the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God and its Righteouſneſs, that we may have his Knowledge, and all other things with it, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6 33. Whereas theſe Preach and Write as though Salvation were but to be in a glorious Place, and as though a Soul, even without knowledge, were happy by admittance thereinto: that is to ſay, as though Heaven and Hell were local; And as they make God's Knowledge different from Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34920:4"/>ſo they make the means of God's Knowledge quite another thing than the means of Salvation, and then the Scriptures make them, to wit, good Natural Parts, and going to School to earn of the Doctors and their Books; which things the Scripture diſowns, as we ſhall ſee hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>But if it be ſo, that is, If the means of Salvation be quite other things than theſe; and if they and Salvation it ſelf be an unknown thing; and it concerns us to learn the way to Life Eternal, it is well worth our while to hear and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire what the Scriptures ſay of them, and what both Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and its means, Religion, are.</p>
            <p>Salvation, Eternal Life, or the Kingdom of God, or of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, for theſe are all one thing, as it appears from <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. 11-13.11. conferr'd with <hi>Mark</hi> 4.11. and <hi>Luke</hi> 7.28-8.10. is <hi>to know,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 17.3. <hi>God, and him whom he hath ſent;</hi> or conſiſteth in the true Knowledge of God, or Wiſdom, according to the Scriptures, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.13. conferr'd with <hi>Luke</hi> 11.52. And as even the Heathen Philoſophers acknowledge, who unanimouſly make Wiſdom the <hi>Summum Bonum;</hi> and the way to it Silence; <hi>Abſtractio ab externis,</hi> or inward Recollection with a Purification from all that defiles the Soul. And it muſt be ſo indeed, that is, Knowledge or Wiſdom muſt be Man's <hi>Summum Bonum,</hi> if the end for which Mankind was created be Wiſdom; and if Wiſdom be his Reſt, or the <hi>Nonplus ultra</hi> of his ſtate of Perfection. 1. That Wiſdom is the end for which Man was created, is confeſſed on all hands, by owning (what all Sects do) That he was created that he might know the Wonders of the great Wiſdom of God (which he cannot do without being fill'd with all Wiſdom) thereby to be raviſhed with Joy and Admiration, like the Queen of <hi>Sheba,</hi> 1 <hi>King</hi> 10.5. at the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of them: there being nothing ſo ſweet as the New Diſcoveries, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:34920:4"/>the taſte of true knowledge; and thus become partakers of God's own <hi>Summum Bonum: Diviſum Imperium cum</hi> Jove Caeſar <hi>habet:</hi> All thoſe that Chriſt hath made Kings and Prieſts to God his Father, <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.6. both partake of God's Nature, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. <hi>and ſhare the Kingdom with God, Revel.</hi> 2.26, 27. with 3.21.</p>
            <p>And Secondly, Wiſdom is the <hi>Nonplus ultra,</hi> or reſt, or perfect ſtate of Mankind; for in that ſtate (of Wiſdom) God himſelf who cannot err, pronounced him very Good, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.31. in Latine, <hi>Summe Bonus;</hi> which word, as it excludes all defect and imperfection, it implies his perfect State, and that he had attained by thus being very good to his greateſt Perfection, or higheſt degree of Bliſs he could ever pretend to. And that Wiſdom was the ſtate in which he was pronounced and declared very Good, I prove thus: The ſtate in which God declares him very Good, is the very ſame ſtate as God created him in; <hi>but he was created after the Image of God,</hi> v. 27. <hi>Which Image conſiſts,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, in Knowledge,</hi> Coloſ. 3. 10. <hi>and Righteouſneſs,</hi> Epheſ 4.24. both which make up together one thing, which is true Wiſdom; Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom being not a bare Theory, as ſhall be ſhewed: Therefore he was created in Wiſdom, and ſo Wiſdom is the ſtate in which he was ſaid very Good or Perfect, or his ſtate of Perfection. But this was ſaid of <hi>Adam,</hi> and what is it to the reſt of Mankind? Some will argue. It is full as much to them as to him, I anſwer. Becauſe the purpoſe of God is ſtill, that Man ſhould be ſuch: for God being for ever both all Wiſe and Almighty, <hi>his Purpoſe ſtands,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul;</hi> though Man did not ſtand himſelf; and his Gifts and his Calling being without Repentance, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.29. his Will is that his Good Gift, whereof ſee <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.4. <hi>Luke</hi> 11.13. or Donative, which he made to Man ſhould continue ſtill; that Mankind by being Wiſe, or as Gods, <hi>Gen.</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:34920:5"/>3.5. ſhould be ſaved, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. or made again very good and perfect, as <hi>Adam</hi> was, and even as his Father, <hi>which is in Heaven,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.48. Therefore in the <hi>Epheſians</hi> 4.13. and in the <hi>Hebrews</hi> 11.40. St. <hi>Paul</hi> taking this thing for granted, ſaith, <hi>That the Saints he ſpeaks of,</hi> v. 12. <hi>who are to be perfected or ſaved,</hi> will all of them come unto a Perfect Man, and even to the meaſure of the full ſtature of Chriſt, who is yet far more perfect than the firſt Man ever was; <hi>Whence he became the Author of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Salvation or Perfection in others,</hi> Heb. 5.9 Having been ſubſtituted in the place of the firſt Man, that he might mend and redreſs all that he had done amiſs; and reſtore all things again to that ſtate of Perfection which both he (the firſt <hi>Adam</hi>) and the World with him fell from, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.20, 21. and ſo be himſelf <hi>Adam,</hi> that is, the right man who is the true Father of Mankind; begetting Mankind a new by his Spirit of Wiſdom, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.45. Therefore it is that he is called the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> and that St <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>that all the Saints ſhall bear his Image,</hi> v. 49. and not that of the firſt man. Chriſt adds to this in <hi>Matthew</hi> 5.48. ſaying, <hi>be therefore per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect even as your heavenly Father himſelf is perfect,</hi> Hence, ſeeing the Perfection or the full Stature of Chriſt is the ſame (and greater to) as the firſt man <hi>Adam</hi> was at firſt created in, and conſiſteth in Wiſdom; and ſeeing that we muſt come to it in being ſaved; it follows that we muſt come to Wiſdom to be ſaved, and that Wiſdom is the reſt or Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Mankind, beyond which he cannot go, or be further exalted. And by a conſequence drawn <hi>a contrario</hi> from this it follows that Ignorance is the <hi>ſummum málum,</hi> Hell, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the moſt imperfect ſad and diſmal State of Mankind: <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> people are deſtroyed for lack of Knowledge,</hi> ſay the Prophets <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.6. Of which Ignorance of his, becauſe puts him in mind of the Deſpicableneſs, Nakedneſs, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery his fall hath reduced him to <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.17. he cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:34920:5"/>to hear without ſome ſhame and horror; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no Man can bear to be called ignorant, or a Fool with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Anger. But of this <hi>Summum Malum,</hi> we are cured or healed by <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.15. for he brings along with him ſuch <hi>healing in his Wings, Mal</hi> 4.2. as a good <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.20. to cure us of our groſs brutiſh Ignorance of God. Salvation being nothing but a Cure, and a riſing from the deadly Lethargy which Man is fallen into, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.21-5.3. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.49. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.23. <hi>Job</hi> 11.12. <hi>To the light of Life, that is eternal Life, proceeding from the Sun of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which Light is the Life of Man,</hi> John 1.4. <hi>And by that Light or Knowledge which he brings we are ſaved or made Juſt,</hi> Iſai 53.11-11.9. That is to ſay, Righteous and Good, or Perfect; Salvation or Perfection; being Righteouſneſs it ſelf, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17. And by Knowledge, Grace, and Peace, or the Righteouſneſs and Peace which the Kingdom of Heaven and Salvation conſiſts in, are multiplied within us, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Luke</hi> 17.11. Whence we have ſome Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of being fed with Knowledge, <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.15. And that Chriſt ſhould be a Light, who by giving that Knowledge which <hi>Luke</hi> 1.77. calls on this account, <hi>The Knowledge Salvation,</hi> or by <hi>opening the blind Eyes,</hi> and <hi>bringing out of Priſon them that ſit there in darkneſs and in the ſhadow of of Death, would ſave the Jews and Gentiles,</hi> Iſa. 49.6-42.6. <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.79. Wherefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls the Light <hi>the Inheritance of Saints,</hi> Coloſſ. 1.12. being what God promiſed <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Seed ſhould inherit, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.4, 5. <hi>Luke</hi> 24.49. And St. <hi>John</hi> 1.4. ſaith, that their Life is the Light they have in them. For which Reaſon the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures call them the <hi>Children of Light;</hi> and Eternal Death or Hell they entitle outward Darkneſs, as being oppoſed to the Light of the Kingdom of God in the Soul of Man, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.21. Though Hell be ſomething beſides Darkneſs, to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:34920:6"/>wit, the gnaſhing of Teeth, by reaſon of the gnawing and corroding of the Worm, or of a ſharp, auſtere, grim and dark Fire for ever. <hi>O houſe of</hi> Jacob <hi>come ye and let us walk in the Light, or True Knowledge of the Lord,</hi> ſaith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 2.5.42.6.<note place="margin">Note, by the by: All the Sects which have no more Knowledge of God than the <hi>Papiſts</hi> have, are as like the Church of Chriſt, as the Kingdom of Darkneſs is like the Kingdom of God. <hi>Wo be to thee</hi> Chorazin; <hi>Wo be to thee</hi> Bethſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da! <hi>For if the</hi> Papiſts <hi>could hear, and were permitted to read what you may both read and hear,</hi> to wit, what Salvation and Religion conſiſt in, they would give over mumbling of their Beads, and caſting off their Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Hoods, Surplices, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> embrace and follow the means of Wiſdom and Salvation at another rate than you do.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now this Light or this Knowledge, which Salvation conſiſts in, is not a Knowledge in part; nor that great heap of Notions, fine Fancies, Precepts and Rules which many Ingenious Men gather from other Mens Books, or bring forth of their own Heads; but it is Wiſdom it ſelf, or the knowledge of all Truth: Wiſdom being properly an Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Knowledge, or a Light that ſhews all things, <hi>Guides a man into all truth,</hi> John 16.13. and makes all things ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt. It is not a bare <hi>Noſce te ipſum,</hi> or the Knowledge of thy ſelf, nay of the World, that conſtitutes the Wiſdom which makes our Salvation, but the true Knowledge of God and of Jeſus whom he ſends, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19, 20. Becauſe God being in all, and through all, and beyond all the Heavens Circumference, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.6. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.27. and all having its being in, and out of God himſelf, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.28. Nature being as it were a <hi>Naſcitura Dei,</hi> or God bringing forth a part of himſelf out of himſelf, God comprehends all Beings, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.15. And ſo his Knowledge alſo includes all other
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:34920:6"/>Knowledge, not only that of himſelf, and of all the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Kingdom of Heaven, but much more that of the World, ſince it is but as it were an Epitome of God; which beſides is felt and ſeen, <hi>John.</hi> 3.12.</p>
            <p>Chriſt adds, <hi>John</hi> 17.3. unto the Knowledge of God, that of Jeſus Chriſt, as being ſent to refreſh or comfort, and perfect Men, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19, 20. <hi>John</hi> 14.18. Becauſe Chriſt being the Light both of God and of the World, which, like the Sun in the World, both enlighteneth and ſtrengtheneth, and brings Life to Perfection, ſo tempering, allaying, and mitigating the force and fierceneſs of the Fire (which is the Father of Life, giving Life its beginning or a principle of Motion) that it turns the Wrathful Ardor of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (for the Father by himſelf, without the Light of the Son, is a conſuming Fire, from whence he calls himſelf ſo, and an Angry Jealous God, <hi>viz.</hi> in the Creatures only, and by no means in himſelf; for God is <hi>Quatenus</hi> God, that is, Three Perſons in One, nothing but Light, Love, Meekneſs, Joy, and the <hi>Summum Bonum</hi>) into a pleaſant Being or Refrigeratory; thus bringing to Perfection the anxious Firy Soul, or the Life of the Soul which the Father had begun; it behoves us to know him for ſuch Savior, that is, for him that enlighteneth, comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and perfecteth and brings to a pleaſant reſt, the anxious Firy Souls, by introducing his Light into their Fire, which is the Life and Father thereof.</p>
            <p>Now this Knowledge of the Truth which ſaves Man, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.4. ſaves him, ſaith <hi>Chriſt, John</hi> 8.32, 34. <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.26. by freeing him from his Luſts, and the Slavery of Sin. But to be freed he muſt ſight againſt them, and overcome, that by his overcoming he might Reign Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.21. (that is an abſolute King, who hath all at his command that his Kingdom can afford) in God, who is the fulneſs of all things, in all places ſoever, where
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:34920:7"/>ſuch Man is, or finds himſelf when he dies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.25. ſo that he hath where he is, without changing his old place to come into a new one, all Pleaſures for evermore. It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nonſence to think that the Kingdom of God is in a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular place: For this World ſhall paſs away, and when this Body dies, the World diſappeareth, or dies alſo to the Souls (underſtand the Bleſſed Souls) leaving nothing about them but God, the infinite Space, who therefore, as infinite, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit neither quantity, nor time, nor ubiquity. I ſay, that Man muſt fight and overcome to be freed: For, as I ſaid, Wiſdom, or the Knowledge that makes Free, is not a meer paſſive Theory, or bare Notion, but altogether active: For, as one hath defin'd it, Wiſdom is <hi>Lumen mentis</hi> (if not rather <hi>Mens ipſa,</hi> which Chriſt reſtores to the Soul, 1 <hi>John</hi> 520.) <hi>Clarè praelucens tribus ill is facultatibus quae ſimul con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituunt humanam creaturam:</hi> Which Three are, <hi>Intellect us, Voluntas, &amp; Animus.</hi> That is, A Light ſhining firſt to the Intellect, to ſee, or perceive, and underſtand in ſeeing and in hearing, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.14. every thing perfectly: next to the Will; directing and inducing him to chuſe or determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate it ſelf, to deſire and appete only what the Intellect ſhews him to be very good: And laſtly, to the Courage, that is to the power, force and vertue of the Soul, ſtrengthening or enabling it to reduce into Practice, and to follow and perform thoſe things the Underſtanding hath ſhewed to be very good, and which the Will deſires, appetes, and chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth for ſuch. As all things are matured, or ripened and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected by the ſtrength of the Light of the Sun acting in them: So Wiſdom is compleated, and the Soul is perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the power and the ſtrength of its Light, to act and do what it knows fit to be done. A Man's Wiſdom is known in the World by his Actions: <hi>Whence,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>James, I will ſhew thee my Faith by my Works:</hi> That is, I will ſhew thee by them my Knowledge of God; becauſe <hi>Intelligere</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:34920:7"/>being <hi>ipſum credere,</hi> as <hi>Triſinegiſtus</hi> affirms, Faith is an Underſtanding, or <hi>an Evidence,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> Heb 11.1. <hi>of things not ſeen with the Eye,</hi> which therefore are evident or as manifeſt to us as if we ſaw and felt them: So that being convinced of their Truth, we believe them, and live ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that Conviction, doing all that is fit to make us capable of the enjoyment of them. Like the Man in the Goſpel, who underſtanding full well, that there was a great Treaſure hidden in a Neighbours Field, ſold all things, parted with all that he had to purchaſe it. Therefore, <hi>the Juſt,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul, lives by Faith,</hi> like <hi>Abraham,</hi> who would not take any thing, becauſe he knew that it is God's Bleſſing makes a Man Rich, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14. 23. and relied on him for it: And like <hi>Enoch,</hi> who walked as having God in his ſight, <hi>Chap.</hi> 5.24. and the Prophet <hi>Elijah,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>As the Lord liveth, whom I have ſtill preſent, or before whom I ſtand,</hi> 1 Kings 17. 1-18.15. and endeavour to pleaſe to, like a Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er before him whom he looks for Favour, and expects his Fortune from. The Faith that ſaves Man, is not an hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Belief of Chriſt being the Saviour of the World, and of his Death, Paſſion, and Reſurrection; but a doing and acting the things that he bids us do, <hi>viz.</hi> to deny our ſelves, and die with him our ſelves to all the Luſts of the Fleſh. For he believes not in One, who acts point blank contrary to what he ſaith and preſcribes, and takes quite another way than that he ſheweth and teacheth. Not the bare Notion of God, but Righteouſneſs and Power makes the Salvation of Man, or conſtitute God's Kingdom, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.20. And Righteouſneſs and Knowledge reform us to God's Image, and are that Knowledge of God which makes our Salvation, and conſtitutes true Wiſdom. To do Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Juſtice, <hi>is to know me,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 22. 15, 16. And contrary wiſe to do evil, and forbear to do good Works, is not to know God, <hi>Chap.</hi> 9.3, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2 12.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:34920:8"/>
            <p>Having ſeen that the Kingdom of God, or the Salvation of Man conſiſts in Wiſdom; and alſo the <hi>Quid,</hi> or what Wiſdom or God's Knowledge is: It is time to enquire the <hi>Per quid,</hi> or by what means it comes and is obtained. The Scriptures ſay, <hi>That Wiſdom is God's Gift; that he ſend it, and that out of his Mouth comes Knowledge and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> Prov. 2.6. <hi>Job</hi> 32.8. <hi>James</hi> 1.5, 17. For indeed no other thing but the Inſpiration or Breath of the Almighty, the <hi>Spiraculum Vitae,</hi> which he breathed at firſt into the firſt Mans Noſtrils, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.7. and is the Lamp of the Lord, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20. 27. can reform Mankind again to God's Image in Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; or give him that Breath of Life which his Fall bereft him of. The Text ſaith, <hi>Niſchmah Chajim;</hi> that is to ſay, Breath of Lives, becauſe when Man is born again of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, he lives of a threefold Life, to wit, Divine, Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and that which he hath common with the Beaſts, from the Spirit of the World, and from the Stars. Now, what can that Breath of God be but his Holy Spirit, who is the good Gift of God, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.13. with <hi>Matth.</hi> 7 11. which he beſtows on Mankind. <hi>To guide him into all Truth,</hi> John 16.13. <hi>And to teach him all things,</hi> Chap. 14.26. both Natural and Divine; the word <hi>all</hi> comprehending <hi>Omnia Scibilia,</hi> and chiefly natural things, as being <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, ſtanding more open and expoſed to our Senſes and Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, <hi>John.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20. than the Divine Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. For in this Spirit conſiſts the Kingdom of God it ſelf, <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.7. or Salvation or Wiſdom; and without him, Man remains ſtill in his outward Darkneſs, is ſtill a natural Man, <hi>Job</hi> 11.12. Whoſe Reaſon cannot fathom either the things of Nature or of the Kingdom of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. till, by being born again of Water, he becomes fit for the Birth of this Spirit; which makes him again, of that brutiſh Man he was become, an Angelical Creature, <hi>Luke</hi> 20.36. or as Wiſe as the Angels, and <hi>Adam</hi> before he fell. Therefore
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:34920:8"/>when Chriſt (<hi>the expreſs Image of God,</hi> Heb. 1.3.) <hi>came to ſave,</hi> or to reform Man again, he breathed on his Diſciples (they that learn of him) ſaying, <hi>Receive ye the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> Joh. 20.22. to ſhew us that he ſaves Man, by Inſpiring into him the ſame former Breath which God breathed into his Noſtrils; this Inſpiration being the only means of Wiſdom, which he really gives to him; and not as the <hi>Prieſts of Rome</hi> do when they Baptize Children, or rather when they Ape Chriſt (by repeating of his words, and acting this part of his Hiſtory) in the Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>There is a Spirit in Man which is, like a ſmoaking Flax, fit to catch at this new Flame: and the Inſpiration of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, ſaith one of <hi>Job</hi>'s Friends, <hi>Job</hi> 32.8. is that which gives Man Light or Underſtanding. And becauſe it is God's Gift, therefore all the True Chriſtians are ſaid to be <hi>Taught of God, John</hi> 6.45. and to be made by Chriſt Prieſts, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Revel.</hi> 1.6. that is, able to teach them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: For Teaching under the Law was the Office of the Prieſts, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 44.23. <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.7. Whence Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.10. That they have but one Maſter, to wit, himſelf. Then when they have received this Spirit, and not before, they are the Anointed ones, that is, True Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans indeed; for it is the true Unction, or the true Oyl of Gladneſs, whereof that which Kings and Prieſts were of old Anointed with, was a Sign or Sacrament; becauſe Oyl is all Spirit, or the moſt Spiritual part of all Concretes in the World. And are ſaid <hi>to know all things,</hi> 1 John 2.20. and not to need to be taught any thing of any Man, <hi>verſe</hi> 27. So that they need not Travel from home into far Countreys, nor to the Academies to confer with the learned; for God finds Fault with ſuch means, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.30. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.13. and ſhews we muſt paſs from them, <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.4. to find what the Soul loves beſt, its <hi>Summum Bonum,</hi> Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: no Doctors, though never ſo Learned, being capable
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:34920:9"/>to give it, or procure it for any beſides themſelves. Becauſe ſeeing God gives it, they have it not in their gift: nay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſeek for Fame and Applauſe, <hi>John</hi> 5.44. and for Riches and Greatneſs, or Preſerment, inſtead of Tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (which the Diſciples of chriſt ſhould look after in the world, <hi>chap.</hi> 16.33.) and thus, as ſaith <hi>Jeremy</hi> 5.5. break the yoke, and burſt the bonds, they have it not for themſelves, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29.14. <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.25. and therefore rather abuſe the poor Soul, <hi>ſmite it, wound it, take from it</hi> its ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king flax, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.7. than give it any new light, it is but in vain for us to hope for any from them; and very abſurd to look for our Felicity, Wiſdom, from their Predicables. <hi>Non eſt qui ſuſtentet &amp; qui conducat eam inter omnes filios quos ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuit &amp; nutrit:</hi> There is not one capable to feed, guide and hold her up in all the Armies of Sons (whereof ſee <hi>Luke</hi> 21.20, with <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.15.) which ſhe hath bred and brought forth, ſaith the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> 51.18, 20: when he ſaw in the ſpirit the ſtate of the preſent Church. And yet they all ſay we ſee, <hi>John</hi> 9.41. ſo much its deſolation is become abominable. The word of wiſdom alone which is nigh in our hearts, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.8. ſpringing up there like the ſeed left to it ſelf in the ground, and growing we know not how, <hi>Mark</hi> 4.27. and which word is Chriſt himſelf, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.1. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24. being that which gives knowledge; <hi>Blando ſno ſuſurro,</hi> by his ſtill ſmall voice in us, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 19.12. even the Learned themſelves of the world being Judges, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.31. for their own experience may, if they pleaſe to think on't, abundantly convince them that they never come to know, or to have any knowledge, whil'ſt they go to hear others, and till paſſing from, that is, ceaſing from all School Learning, and all things without themſelves, they retire in themſelves, and meditate by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, like <hi>Iſaac, Gen.</hi> 24.63. and all wiſe men: thus ſtirring up, or making good uſe of the ſmoaking flax, or ſpirit which
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:34920:9"/>is in them, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.6. and of which all Mankind hath enough to profit withal, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25 15.</p>
            <p>Having fully proved that this Spirit muſt be had of all thoſe who deſire to have or obtain Wiſdom, that is to ſay, Salvation: I muſt here demonſtrate, to prevent an Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that all Men may obtain it, if they will but improve their Talent or Trade with it: what I muſt do likewiſe by the means of the Scriptures. The Scripture declares that <hi>God gives this ſpirit of wiſdom to all that ask it of him,</hi> Luke 11.13. Jam. 1.5. and that will, ſaith St. <hi>Peter,</hi> Acts 2. 38-3.19, 20. enter into Repentance. And this, as much as it was given to the Apoſtles, that is, if they overcome, and in caſe they follow Chriſt in the Regeneration, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.28-20.23. <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.21. as much as the Apoſtles and primitive Chriſtians did; for it being the bleſſing promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and to <hi>Adam</hi> before him, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.4, 5. <hi>Luke</hi> 24.49. it belongs to as many of their Children, as the Lord ſhall ever call, ſaith <hi>Peter,</hi> Acts 2.38, 39. that is, to as many as prepare themſelves for it, or ſet themſelves in order, the Text ſaith <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.48. with ſuch preparation as I ſhall ſpeak of, and ſhew in its time and place: and this, not only, adds he, <hi>chap.</hi> 10.47-11.15. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>even as;</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, <hi>after the manner that we have it our ſelves</hi> (he means all the Apoſtles) <hi>the Lord,</hi> (going on further in confirmation of this, <hi>ver.</hi> 9.) <hi>putting no ſuch difference</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> of an ordinary and extraordinary gift) <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us</hi> (the Apoſtles) <hi>and the other Believers,</hi> as the Lip-Chriſtian's device: <hi>but giving the Holy Ghoſt to all indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:</hi> yet in proportion to what degree of true Faith he knows every Believer hath, <hi>ver.</hi> 8 that is as much as to <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> if he believes in Chriſt as much as they did: as it is evident from <hi>Cornelius</hi> his houſhold, <hi>chap.</hi> 10.44. and from the reſt of them that believed in the Word, <hi>chap.</hi> 19.6. And becauſe it is the thing promiſed to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and to his Seed for ever,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:34920:10"/>
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 13.15-17.7, 19. (for neither the <hi>Jews</hi> nor we can name any other thing that doth anſwer this Promiſe:) St, <hi>Paul</hi> calls it the Spirit of Promiſe, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.14. And ſpeaks always as taking it for granted, that all the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Churches of <hi>Antioch, Acts</hi> 13.52. of <hi>Epheſus, Chap,</hi> 2.17, 18-3.6-5.18. of <hi>Galatia,</hi> 3.2, 3, 5, 14-5.5, 16, 25. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11, 19. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.14. <hi>Rome</hi> 5.5. 8.11, 23. <hi>Philipi</hi> 3.3. <hi>Coloſſus</hi> 1.8-3.10. And of <hi>Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonica,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ</hi> 1.5-5.19. 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2 13. received, or might receive after wards, the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>So that ſeeing that all Men may obtain the Gift of it, and ſeeing that Salvation cannot be had without it, it being, as I ſaid, the <hi>Perquid</hi> of Salvation; we are bound, that is to ſay, as many of us as will, or intend to be Saved, to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to get it; and therefore to enquire after the <hi>Quomodo.</hi> or right way to procure it; that is, trade with, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove our Talent ſo well, as to gain many more with it. Which Enquiry muſt be made, like the reſt, in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>I have ſaid already, That as Men make Salvation different from God's Knowledge, ſo they make the means of God's Knowledge, or of true Wiſdom, different from this Spirit; to wit, good Natural Parts, and their own Reaſon and Wit; and conſequently they know of no other way to it, but hard ſtudy in the Schools, and Conſulting their Maſters and their Learned Doctors Books: As if the Wiſdom of God could be had out of thoſe things, and could be confined to the narrow pale of their Rules! Whereas on the contrary, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures teach, that the Man who will be Learned and Wiſe, <hi>muſt become a Fool,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. <hi>a Child, Matth.</hi> 18.3. That is, deſpond, like a Child, of his Wit, Parts, and Learning. Except you become as ſimple, <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.22. and humble as little Children, who are not ſelf-conceited, and have no prejudice againſt what their Teachers ſay, and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:34920:10"/>not againſt it, but only amongſt themſelves, ſtriving who ſhall learn it beſt; you ſhall remain in Darkneſs, or never ſee God's Kingdom, <hi>Chap.</hi> 18.4. <hi>Luke</hi> 18.17. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God keeps from the Wiſe and Prudent, who ſay we ſee, <hi>John</hi> 9 41. all true Wiſdom and Knowledge, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veals the ſame only to humble, ſingle-eyed Babes, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11. 25. And it will ever be ſo, becauſe Witneſs Truth himſelf, <hi>v.</hi> 26. <hi>John</hi> 14.6. it is God's Will and Pleaſure that it ſhould always be ſo; whatever the great Doctors, who would be wiſer than Chriſt, therefore blow their Noſe at him, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.4. in <hi>Greek</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, may ſay to the contrary. <hi>The meek will he guide in judgment, and the meek and lewly in heart will he teach his ways,</hi> Pſal. 25.9. Wherefore <hi>bleſſed are the meek, and they that rule their Spirit,</hi> Prov. 16.32. <hi>For they ſhall inherit the Earth,</hi> Matth. 5.5. And Wiſdom it ſelf. <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>Take my yoke upon you,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Chap.</hi> 11.29. That is, learn of me that I am lowly in heart, and you ſhall come to the Reſt or Perſection of your Souls. O how happy is the Man that bears Chriſt's Yoke from his Youth!</p>
            <p>The Scriptures teach us further, That God's Fear is not only the beginning, but the end, or a Treaſure of Wiſdom, <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.6. That all they that keep God's Word have ſuch an Underſtanding, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.10. That they know a great deal more than all their Wiſeſt Teachers, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.99, 100, 104. And that God layeth up Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for them that are Righteous, <hi>Prov.</hi> 2. 7. <hi>Meeting,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 64.5. <hi>them that work Righteouſneſs, and that do delight in it: For if any Man will do God's Will,</hi> John 7.17. Keep the words of Chriſt, <hi>Chap.</hi> 14.23. God will love him, and meet him, or come by the Holy Ghoſt, and make his abode with him, as he met <hi>Cornelius, Acts</hi> 10.44. becauſe he feared God, and wrought Righteouſneſs, <hi>verſe</hi> 35. So that the Fear of God is the way wherein what gives Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is to be met with; and ſo is the <hi>Quomodo</hi> of Wiſdom
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34920:11"/>or Salvation. Now to Fear God is the ſame as to do the Will of God; and to do the Will of God implies <hi>a ceaſing from Man,</hi> that is to ſay, a ceaſing from doing the will of Man, or being born of the Fleſh, <hi>John</hi> 1.13. as being againſt God's Will, and at Enmity with him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8 7. and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently implies a dying to our ſelves, that we may be born of, and live to, the Will of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.11. that is, implies ſuch Self-denial, or abſtinence from all the things which our natural Life deſires, as makes us as dead to it, as they that are no more living, or have loſt their Life. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the corn of Wheat,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 12.24, 25. <hi>fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ground and die, it brings forth no fruit;</hi> ſo the way for Man to keep his Life to Eternal Life, is to hate it, or ceaſe from the Life he hath <hi>of this World:</hi> or, as he ſaith in <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> 16.25. <hi>to loſe it;</hi> that is, to die. And in <hi>John</hi> 3.3. He ſaith further, <hi>Except a man be born again,</hi> and that, <hi>of Water,</hi> V. 5. <hi>he cannot ſee God's Kingdom;</hi> that is, receive the Spirit which conſtitutes God's Kingdom, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17. Now to be born again, is to begin to have a ſecond or a new Life: A ſecond Life implies a dying to the former There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt die before we be born again and live, to wit, of the Life that ſaves: and we muſt be born again to live, and that of Water. So that two things, a dying, and a new birth of Water, are neceſſary to Life, and the only way through which we muſt unavoidably paſs to come to Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, or to the perfect new Birth of the Spirit of Wiſdom; in which latter Birth chiefly conſiſts our Salvation. Which things, <note place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Wall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> his Sermons of Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration. Printed for Mr. <hi>Rogers</hi> at the <hi>Sun</hi> near <hi>Temple Bar.</hi>
               </note> becauſe very few Divines do know what they are, and therefore paſs them over, and teach with Dr. <hi>Wallis, That we are not bound to know, and to trouble our ſelves with ſuch nice Enquiries,</hi> as if we were not to be ſaved by coming, ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.4. <hi>to the knowledge of the Truth.</hi> I think fit to declare: and for this end, to begin by the new Birth of Water.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:34920:11"/>
            <p>To be born of Water then, is, not to be Baptized, as we are now with Water, but to take the beginning of our Life from VVater; To do which, man muſt become Water; be Water himſelf: if not in his Fleſh and Bones (as <hi>Nicode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> took it) however within the Heart, that is, in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Man, by making his Heart tender, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.27. and as humble, as reſigned; and in a word as paſſive or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>active as Water. That is to ſay, as Water hath no motion of it ſelf but ſtands ſtill; or, if moved, falls downwards con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually; or flows this way or that way as the Wind agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates it; ſo our Hearts ſhould no more have any will of their own, but lay ſtill as a dead thing, or as being reſolved even to die at God's Feet: That as out of the ſhapeleſs. paſſive, unactive Water, all the Concretes in the World are formed and produced, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3 5. by the only working of God's Spirit upon it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.6. ſo we may, out of that ſtate wherein we have no more any motion, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, luſt, or will of out own, but only that to yield all, and enter into God's Will, receive a new form and ſhaper, or be reformed, or born again of the firſt Spirit that gave <hi>Adam</hi> a true Life, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.7. <hi>after the Image of God;</hi> put off the earthly Image we have from Father <hi>Adam,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 15.49. And thus by Humility riſe again to that ſtate which he and <hi>Eve</hi> fell from by Pride.</p>
            <p>And this is what is ſhewed us by the Water, and the Way of uſing it in Baptiſm. <hi>We are,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 6.4. <hi>by Baptiſm buried with Chriſt into death;</hi> that is, as they which were Baptized in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s time, being cover'd all over when they were dipt in Water, were by this means as it were dead and buried to the World: So we by this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Baptiſm or birth or ſtate of Water, become as dead men, buried to all the Luſts of the Fleſh, and to all Self-will, as Pride, Covetouſneſs, and Envy, and to all the reliance and hope we have on this World; <hi>that as Chriſt,</hi> adds he, <hi>roſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:34920:12"/>up from grave through God's Spirit;</hi> ſo we ſhould out of this ſtate riſe into a new Creature that hath got a Divine Form, which is riſing from the Dead, and the firſt Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All is made out of Spirit (or, as</hi> Hippocrates <hi>ſaith, in</hi> pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo de Diaeta, <hi>out of Fire) and Water.</hi> Spiritus eſt organum in manu ſummi Dei, quo agitantur omnes in hoc mundo ſpecies, <hi>ſaith</hi> Triſmegiſtus <hi>of it. Which Spirit coming down firſt from the Stars into the Air, and thence into the Water, works on it continually: whence an Oil is produced; and this Oil, by a longer digeſtion, becomes a Salt; which Salt is the firſt Matter and true Body of Concretes. This is demonſtrable from the juices of Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tables, if they be diſtilled before their Fermentation; but better by diſtilling ſome</hi> May-<hi>dew, or Rain-water; becauſe being thin and light, and a tranſparent Liquor, by reaſon of their being circulated in the Air, they are not thought by many to have and contain an Oil, yet in their diſtilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they yield an Oil and a Salt, which muſt have been formed there by the Spirit from the Stars it was impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated with, working upon its Vehicle, the ſaid Dew or Rain-water.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So likewiſe Man being made of Water, and of Spirit, muſt be born again of them to become a new Creature; and muſt firſt become water, make his heart ſoft and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; break that Rock, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did, <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.6. and melt the Ice or hardneſs of his heart into water, or the tears of Repentance, that by the Holy Spirit, which is the Dew, the Manna, or the true Bread from Heaven that gives life unto the world, <hi>John</hi> 6.32, 33. an Oil firſt, and then a Salt, which is the true Fleſh and Blood, or the true Body of Chriſt, <hi>ver.</hi> 51. and alſo the new Body the bleſſed Souls ſhall riſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:34920:12"/>with, or our houſe from above, may be formed, produced, and perfected within him. Therefore Chriſt exhorts all Men to have ſome Salt in themſelves, <hi>Mark</hi> 9.50. that is to ſay, as the Salt, underſtand eſſential Salt, is the firſt mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of things, and reſults from the Spirit's action upon the water; ſo all Men ſhould always have ſome of that ſame firſt ſubſtance which the Spirit of God forms in Souls ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in tears, and ſo ſhould give leave to his Spirit to work it in them, and produce by its working a Salt to ſalt them withal, <hi>ver.</hi> 49. or preſerve both their Body and Soul to Eternal Life, from all ſort of Corruption: ſuch as Lepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, which makes the whole Body inſenſible; and as that, thorow hardneſs of heart, which turns Man into ſuch Salt as <hi>Lot</hi>'s Wife was, that is, a Salt <hi>Alkali,</hi> which is gone through the Fire, and therefore can by no means be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wrought upon; for thereby loſing its Oyl, or its Radical Moiſture, the Vehicle of the Spirit, is no more ſuſceptible (as the moiſt eſſential Salt, or Nitre of the Earth, is) of any ſweet influence of Heaven working on it: but becomes a meer dead Coal, a Lime-ſtone, an <hi>Alkali,</hi> made by Incineration; and that melts no more like Ice, and other eſſential Salts, by the warmth of the Spirit, but by a ſtrong fierce Fire into a hard ſtone like Glaſs, which is paſt for evermore all hope of recovery, or of regeneration, and ſo makes Man incapable of ſuch Vegetation as the dry Rod of <hi>Aaron,</hi> by its budding forth again, typified the Souls muſt have. Therefore remember <hi>Lot</hi>'s Wife, <hi>flee from the Land of the North,</hi> this hard froſty, dark, lowring, diſmal, or Northerly ſtate, ſaith the Lord by <hi>Zachary</hi> 2.6. whoever will inhabit or live in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ver. 4.</p>
            <p>This birth of Water therefore is what makes Man ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptible of the ſweet influence and working of God's Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit on his Soul to renew it, and make it grow green and bud, and bear Fruits, or be fruitful; for thereby we do
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:34920:13"/>(like <hi>John</hi> by his Baptiſm of water) prepare the way of the Lord, that is, for the Lord's coming by his comforting Spirit: this birth of water being the true preparation or ordering of the Soul, which in the 15th <hi>Page</hi> I promis'd to ſpeak of. For as good ground is made fit to receive, and to retain the influence of Heaven, or the Spirit that comes down from Heaven into the Air, and the Water and the Earth, (the Scriptures call it the Dew, and the Bleſſing from above, <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.40-49.15.) by its being frequently moiſtned with Rain or Water; ſo our Souls become fit for the Bleſſing promiſed, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28. by being throughly wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd; for the Water being void and empty, (as the Earth was, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.2.) the <hi>Chymiſts</hi> call this nature of the Water, and the Earth an <hi>Alkalick</hi> quality, it is the ſitter to draw and to impregnate it ſelf with the Spirit from the Stars, and ſo to nouriſh the Earth which is well watered with it, by introducing this ſame ſtarry Spirit into it. So the Soul, by reducing it ſelf to water, becomes void and empty like water, that is void of all the cares and deſires of this world, and thereby is the ſitter to be impregnated with the Spirit, or the Seed of heavenly Bridgroom. And wo be to them, ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.19. that are not ſo. prepared, but are already with Child, and give ſuck about the time that the Bridegroom comes to them! becauſe they cannot go in with him to the Marriage Room, and becauſe the door is ſhut, and can no more be opened, <hi>chap.</hi> 25.10. that is, they are ſo hardned, that they become like <hi>Lot</hi>'s Wiſe, or (to continue here the foregoing Metaphor) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come like ſome ſort of ground (which for lack of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent moiſture, turns to Sand and Duſt, and bears no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Bryers, whoſe end is therefore to be burned, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> affirms, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.8.) dry, and bound like clods of earth, or hard for want of moiſture; a deſolate Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.3. yielding nothing but Bryers, and even Duſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:34920:13"/>and Aſhes, or ſuch lixiviate Salt as is made out of Aſhes, or by Incineration, that is a Salt <hi>Alkali.</hi> So that Water, or the Birth, or the Baptiſm of Water, is always, like the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> the Forerunner of the Lord, who comes in the cloudy, ſad, mourning, dark, ignorant Souls, by the light of his Spirit, to revive and comfort them. Whence, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to St. <hi>John</hi> 5.6. he comes by Water and Blood, that is, Water and Spirit; Blood being but a Compound of Water and of Spirit: and ſo do all the Children of <hi>Adam</hi> when they are born, to ſhew them that they muſt be born again of thoſe two things.</p>
            <p>I ſay, that the Lord comes by his comforting Spirit; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe when that Spirit comes, it is the coming of Chriſt promiſed, <hi>John</hi> 14.18, 28-16.22. or the Lord that comes himſelf. Seeing that Jeſus himſelf is he that's ſent, ſaith <hi>Peter, Acts</hi> 3.19, 20-2.38. from the preſence of the Lord; to refreſh or comfort Men; or to be, as St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, 14. 16. their Comforter for ever. And therefore Chriſt is the ſame as the comforting Spirit; and ſo the coming of this, <hi>viz.</hi> of the Holy Spirit, is the ſame as the ſecond coming, or coming again; or, the manifeſtation of Chriſt himſelf promiſed, <hi>John</hi> 14.18, 21. Concerning which, ſee <hi>Math.</hi> 16.28. with <hi>Mark</hi> 9.1. and <hi>Luke</hi> 9.27-24.49. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 15, 16.</p>
            <p>And, I ſay, that he comes into the ſad cloudy Souls: for as the <hi>Lightning,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Math.</hi> 24.27, 30. <hi>appeareth out of tho Eaſt, and ſhineth even unto the Weſt; ſo ſhall the coming of the Son of Man happen in the clouds of Heaven, with power and great glory.</hi> For theſe two <hi>Verſes</hi> may be applied to the ſaid coming of Chriſt by the Holy Ghoſt; Chriſt having reſpect therein to the Diſciples queſtion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in the 3d <hi>Verſe,</hi> concerning his coming again in his day, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.24. that is, when he ſhould be revealed, <hi>ver.</hi> 30. or ſhould come in his Kingdom, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.28. though
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:34920:14"/>perhaps they might not then underſtand it in this ſenſe, but took it, as Men now do, as thô it were meant only of his third and laſt coming, <hi>viz.</hi> at the end of the world. Which Anſwer of Chriſt ſets forth the manner of his Coming, and the qualification of the thing which he comes to; to wit, the cloudy, or ſad and dark, or ignorant Souls, which are the Clouds of Heaven, hiding Heaven within them, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.21. from the ſight of other People. For as the Lightning breaks out of the dark, thick, gloomy Clouds, ſhining through them for a time, then the Cloud cloſeth again; ſo doth his Coming appear in the dark, ſorrowful Souls, <hi>John</hi> 16.20, 22. like a flaſh of Lightning, or ſudden Coruſcation, breaking out of their darkneſs, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. and opening, as it were, the Cloud that envelops them, then ſhuts it ſelf up again; and ſo continueth to do with many Men for ſometime, till at laſt diſſipating the darkneſs alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, it comes to ſhine through and through the Sphere, or the whole Body, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.22. thus ſhining from Eaſt to Weſt all the Hemiſphere over: as it hapned unto Chriſt as his Transfiguration, and as it is, and will be with all the Saints in Glory: who are repreſented therefore with beams about them, becauſe they ſhine like the Stars, and dart out, like the Sun, their beams on every ſide, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.3. <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.43. For a remembrance of which ſlaſhing or coruſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and of the manner of it, the Biſhops wear a Mitre, bearing the ſhape of a Flame; or elſe of thoſe cloven Tongues which were like as of Fire, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.30. to ſignifie the opening of the dark clouds in man's head, and the cleaving (as it were) of the ſutures in the Scull, and man's communication through this cleft part with Heaven: which Mitre they aſſum'd firſt, when this flaſhing or lightning began to ceaſe in the Church, leſt the remembrance it ſelf of it ſhould be loſt alſo. But that it cloſeth not up as the Crown of a King doth, ſignified, that their flaſhing did not
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:34920:14"/>ſhine through on all ſides; that it was but beginning or juſt breaking out in them; and that it continued not with them, as with crowned Heads: and therefore that they ought not to pretend to, and aſcribe to themſelves ſo much honour in the Church as Kings may do; and conſequently much leſs than they in temporal things, eſpecially ſeeing that the Kingdom of Chriſt, witneſs himſelf, <hi>John</hi> 18.36. is not of this world. And hence it may be gather'd, that the Church was yet modeſt when they begun to wear it: But now the Mitre is got higher than the Crown itſelf, and lords it over Princes and Kings both in Church and State. Which is not well done, my Sons, my incorrigible Sons, would old <hi>Eli</hi> ſay to them, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.24. if he were alive again; you ought not thus to break Chriſt's Yoke, and to burſt his Bonds, if you will be his Diſciples, or his true Church in <hi>England:</hi> and you may chance to pay for it, if you hearken not to the voice of your Father, <hi>ver.</hi> 25. <hi>For he that being often reproved, hardneth his neck, ſhall ſuddenly be deſtroyed, and that without remedy,</hi> Prov. 3 34-29.1. of which you have a very freſh Inſtance in the late King.</p>
            <p>To return to the manner of the ſecond Coming of Chriſt by the Holy Ghoſt; obſerve, that <hi>as the lightning comes</hi> at firſt <hi>out of the Eaſt, and then ſhines even unto the Weſt,</hi> that is, enlightneth the Hemiſphere all over; ſo his Coming (which is not with any obſervation, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.20.) appears firſt like the Day-ſpring, <hi>chap.</hi> 1.78. or the dawning of the day; or is like the morning Star ariſing in our hearts, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. for there all our thoughts, or firſt glimpſes of Light riſe: then encreaſing more and more to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect light or day, <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.18. it comes to be like the Sun at Noon, and at the Solſtice: in reference to both which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct ſtates, Chriſt is called <hi>the Morning Star,</hi> by St. <hi>John, Rev.</hi> 22.16, 20. and <hi>the Sun of Righteouſneſs,</hi> by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:34920:15"/>
               <hi>Malachy,</hi> 4.2. becauſe he both diſſipates the Morning Clouds by his light, and ſtrengthneth by the power of it a Believer ſo that he brings him to ripeneſs, or to his full perfection: the flaſh at his appearance ſhining nothing near ſo bright and comfortable as the Sun, and as itſelf would do if it laſted for ever, or endured a great while without vaniſhing again. For after the ſame manner Chriſt, the Word, or the Wiſdom, and Light, and Power of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24. within us, in our hearts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10 8. ſpringing out of the centre, out of a man's own darkneſs, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. firſt appears to the ſad mind like glimmering ſparks of light, which are a great refreſhing to the Soul; light or knowledge bringing ſtill along with it great joy, as I have ſaid. Then encreaſing, and ſending its ſweet beams by little and little towards the Circumſerence, till it ſhines through the whole Sphere, it enligthneth all over, and at the ſame time comforts and ſtrengthneth ſick ſaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Man, in ſuch ſort that he may riſe from the ſhadow of death, (wherein he lay as benumm'd) and walk, and run, and not faint, and mount up with wings as Eagles, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.31. <hi>Joel</hi> 2.7. and going from ſtrength to ſtrength, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.7. both take God's Kingdom by force, and riſe to the very top or crown, or zenith thereof, which is God's holy mountain, or the higheſt ſtate of bliſs, and of glory, and of light, which Mankind is capable of, <hi>Dan</hi> 12.3. <hi>Mat.</hi> 13, 43.-19.28. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21. continuing all the while ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſhining, enlightning, and refreſhing the firy dark Soul to eternal life, with the water of that Well, that is, Wiſdom and Knowledge flowing out of a Man's ſelf, whereof Chriſt ſpake in St. <hi>John</hi> 4.14-7.38. As an ever flowing ſpring of living water ſtreaming through a hot and deſart place, would revive the weary Traveller dying for Thirſt; ſo this new Spring of Wiſdom revives the dry, ſainting Soul of <hi>Samſon,</hi> and <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> that is of Chriſt's ſtout Champions,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:34920:15"/>
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.20. (the Church Militant on Earth) as ſoon as they begin to thirſt after Righteouſneſs, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.6 as it was typified by the water guſhing out of the Aſſes dry Jaw-bone, which <hi>Samſon,</hi> after a great Victory, being ready to die, met with in his thirſt, <hi>Judg.</hi> 15.18, 19. and by the Wells of water which <hi>Iſrael</hi> found at laſt in the dry and deſart Land, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.27. But before he, I mean the ſaid ſick Man, comes to this, he muſt dye the ſecond death, according to God's threatning, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. which, becauſe God's Word is true, ſhall not paſs away from him before it be fulfilled, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.35. and this is not ſo eaſie a matter for him to do, as our learned Divines, who paſs it over <hi>ſicco pede,</hi> teach in their Sermons.</p>
            <p>For (to ſpeak of this dying, which is the other thing needful for the obtaining the ſaid birth of the Spirit) it is really a dying; and dying, you will grant, is a hard thing to Mankind: Neither is it only ſuch dying as is that of this body of the fleſh, which Men eaſily go through: But ſuch as is proper and peculiar to the Soul, which is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable, that none but the Son of Man, or at leaſt the Soul of Man, enabled by the virtue and ſtrength of the Son of Man, can ſuſtain or bear with it, <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.14. For no man, he ſaith himſelf, <hi>John.</hi> 3.13. doth aſcend up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, but he that comes down from thence, to give us power and ſtrength, and thus by enabling us to die, lifts us up thither: and there go along with it the terrors of Hell it ſelf. Which thing, becauſe it ſeems new and very ſtrange to the world, is what I do here take upon me to demonſtrate.</p>
            <p>And firſt, to ſhew what it is. This dying, is the ſame death as that <hi>Adam died of</hi> after he had tranſgreſſed, which muſt be ſome other thing than the death of his Body; for he <hi>was ſurely to die the day</hi> that he tranſgreſſed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. whereas his Body did live 900 years after. And that was
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:34920:16"/>a riſing, or an exaſperation of the Fire of his Soul, after he taſted the Apple, (for he had loſt long before, <hi>viz.</hi> before he fell aſleep, the Light of Life, which his Soul enjoyed at his Creation) to a very intenſe or high degree of ſierceneſs; raging in him till the time he catcht hold of the promiſe made to him of the Woman's Seed, Chriſt, the <hi>Light</hi> of the world: For Life without Light, is but a dark and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure Fire, kindled either here or there in ſome individual place, and burning without ſhining, as do all Acids, the Froſt, and thoſe Corroſives, called <hi>Ignes Potentiales</hi> by Chymical Writers; whereby the Life juſt ſubſiſts in a very anxious, fretful ſtate or condition, as being always feeding upon the thing it is in, that is, upon the Body which it had formed itſelf, till that Body be conſum'd, or till this hungry Fire be fully ſatiated. And this Fire thus burning, was repreſented to us by the firy Serpent of God's People in the Deſart, and by a Worm or Serpent, which Chriſt ſaith doth never die, becauſe it is always <hi>renaſcens,</hi> repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing or kindling itſelf anew; <hi>viz.</hi> in the eternal Souls, for there it can as well do it always as for once, by reaſon that its Body or Subject doth not decay, and when exaſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, it is the Death of the Soul, or its Hell, burning, gnawing, and making it for ever anxious, and full of pain; except it reacheth the Light that makes all things comfortable. Here conſider the grimneſs of a dark and froſty Night, which chills, benums, and deſtroys, and burns all things on the ground; and what ſtate things would lay in, if the Light of the Sun were taken out of the world. Would not all the living things lay ſtill like Worms in Winter, and be frozen up as hard and ſtiff as Ice in their place? Sure the world itſelf would be nothing but Death all over! And thence conceive, if you can, how ſharp, ſevere, and bitter are to the deſpairing Soul, whoſe dark Fire corroding and bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it, like ſharp Froſt, or a fretting Humor, or ſome tart,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:34920:16"/>acid Liquor, makes it ake and ſhoot, and prick, and rave, like an angry Sore, beyond imagination; the horrors of that grim Night which the terrible Day of the Lord is ſaid to have, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.3. But when the Light appeareth, and breaks out in this darkneſs, and runs through and over ſpreads this dark, yet burning, Fire: How pleaſant and comfortable it looks! Things grow green again, and look, as the Prophets ſay, like the Garden of the Lord; <hi>Before them the Land is like the Garden of</hi> Eden, <hi>and behind a Flame burneth, and makes all, as it were, a deſolate Wilderneſs:</hi> where the Heat and the Cold kills, burneth, and parcheth all up. For the Light bringing with it the clear and lovely Sunſhine, doth not only mitigate and allay this fierce Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, but turns the Ardor of Heat, and the great ſharpneſs of Cold into a Refrigery, and makes the Soul a pleaſant and delightful Paradiſe. <hi>Ho, ho, come forth, ſaith the Lord,</hi> Zach. 2.6, 7. <hi>flee from the Land of the North;</hi> Zion, <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver thy ſelf out of ſuch Northerly ſtate, and walk in the light of God.</hi> Fire exaſperated, and deprived of all Light, is Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Death or Hell, or the wrath of God, or god burning in the Soul: And the ſame Fire fully ſatiated, tinctured, and impregnated with Light, is the Eternal Life, Reſt, and Paradiſe of the Soul, and God appeaſed, pleaſed, become pleaſant, delightful, gentle and merciful in us, and the love of God itſelf ſhed abroad in our hearts by the Holy Spirit of Chriſt which he gives to us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.5. Note well here what <hi>Matthew</hi> ſaith, 3.17. that it is in Jeſus Chriſt, who is the Light of the world; that God the Father, who is a Fire, is well pleaſed; and that this was ſaid of him after he was baptized, at the ſame time that he was coming out of the water, <hi>ver.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe Man in this world is not altogether bereft of the Light of Life, all Men being enlightned, not only
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:34920:17"/>with the outward, but the inward Light, Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 1.9. And therefore his Life is not a Fire without ſome Light, he hath ſome good of his Life, and enjoys, whil'ſt he lives here, the pleaſures this world affords, without any ſenſible torment or anxiety. Except the Father, who draws always all Men to himſelf, awakes the Worm, and ſtir up and acuate the Fire, which was kept within its bound both by the Light of this world, and by the Senſualities which the Soul is diverted, and which the Worm of the Soul is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways lull'd aſleep with: For then when the Worm awakes, and the Fire is moved, the Soul begins to feel the gnawing <hi>Syndereſes</hi> that bite, rack, and torture it, then Man is in a ſad pickle, his Light goes out, he deſpairs, he cries <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ror, Abſumor;</hi> he looks up, and behold trouble; down, and on every ſide, and behold nothing but pain, anguiſh, darkneſs, and horror. Then his Moon is eclipſed, his Sun, ſaith Chriſt, is darkned, and the Powers of Heaven, or of the Kingdom of God, or of Heaven, within him, are ſhaken, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.28. as it hapned to Chriſt in his Agony, when he ſweated Blood for it, <hi>Luke</hi> 22.44. and was ſorrowful to death; and prayed very fervently, that this Cup (this very death, and not the death of his fleſh, for that's not worth praying for, and it was unavoidable) might paſs from him if poſſible, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.38, 39. And then the ſorrows of Hell compaſs him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.5. and then he bears with Chriſt the wrath of God, ſeels that great tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation foretold, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.21, 22. which none was ever ever like to, and, note well, <hi>never ſhall be;</hi> and which no man in the fleſh could ever go thorow with, except the days of this ſame Tribulation were ſhortned; by the <hi>God of</hi> Jeſu-run, <hi>who comes riding in the clouds of the heaven in his help, and in the great might of his excellency on the sky: For the eternal God is his refuge, and underneath are the everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing arms, to thruſt out the enemies that ſpoil'd him from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:34920:17"/>him,</hi> Deut. 33.26, 27. How ſweet is the Name Jeſus to a Soul that would come out of its <hi>Gall of bitterneſs! Acts</hi> 8.23. In a word, he dies the death, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. and bears the wrath of God; for all men muſt be judged, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.27. or undergo the trial of, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.12. and theſe be the days, ſaith <hi>Luke</hi> 21.22. of vengeance, or of wrath; wherein, as ſaith <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 66.16. the Lord ſhall plead by Fire and by his Sword with all fleſh in this or the other world, for falling away from him. It's a fearful thing to fall into the hands of that God, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.31. who is a Fire living and devouring for ever! <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.14 <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12 29.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It is all Men in the world whom God pleads with, by Fire and by his Sword: for every Man, ſaith <hi>Mark,</hi> 9.49. ſhall be ſalted with Fire: and Chriſt baptizeth as well with Fire, ſaith the Baptiſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.11. as with the holy Spirit thoſe that are to be ſaved. Now the word <hi>every one,</hi> includes all, and excepts none: therefore they that are ſaved, muſt all go through this Fire: this being the Cherubim who keeps with a flaming Sword the way of the Tree of Life, and of Paradiſe itſelf; ſo that there is no coming at them but only through it, that it, through his flaming Sword: at leaſt if the Word of God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 23, 24. is not a meer Hiſtory, and was not written in vain, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.25. but for Inſtruction, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this, <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaking of this trial by Fire, ſaith 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.12. that it is no ſtrange thing happing to the Believers, or thoſe he calls Beloved; and adds in the 13th <hi>verſe,</hi> that they who undergo it partake of Chriſt's ſufferings; which is another proof of the neceſſity of their undergoing it. Firſt he ſaith, 'tis no ſtrange thing: therefore it is an uſual and known thing to the Faithful. Secondly, it did begin at the Apoſtles, and muſt begin at the Houſe of God, <hi>ver.</hi> 17. And Thirdly, they partake, by undergoing of it, of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:34920:18"/>Chriſt's ſufferings and death; which is as much as to ſay, that they muſt undergo it; becauſe it is a chief part of the ſufferings of Chriſt, and they are bound, as appears from <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.24. and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.10 to bear the ſaid ſufferings: being to take up his Croſs, and follow him under it, ſtep by ſtep, through every ſtage or ſlation which he made: (what the ſeveral ſtations, or pitchings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Numb. 21. were a Type and Figure of) and to bear in their body the dying of Jeſus Chriſt: which dying extends ſo far as to the loſs of their life, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.25: ſo long as they have no hopes to find any other way their life, and the life of Chriſt; to the perfection of which they may attain, as was ſaid, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.13. if they do imitate him in this part of his paſſion. For as by his Agony, bloody Sweat, Sorrow to Death, he deſcended into Hell, or bore the wrath of God: and by the reſignation of his will to that of God, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.39, 42. all the while he was ſighting and bearing this <hi>chaſtiſement,</hi> Iſa. 53.5. that is, by his becoming like the Child in <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> 9.6. <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.3. He overcame, and became the wonderful mighty Prince and Champion in our Battels: ſo we, to imitate him in this part of his Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and of his Reſignation, muſt ſight like him, and go through <hi>the Red Sea</hi> of our Blood, that bearing through this great Gulph of God's vengeance and wrath, we may become with him, and with <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 33.28. Kings, Princes, and mighty Champions in God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.6. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out blood, our High Prieſt went not into the ſecond, or moſt Holy Tabernacle, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.7, 8. Without Bloodſhed a Virgin cannot be impregnated: ſo likewiſe a Virgin Soul, that is, which is not with Child, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.19. but is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Chriſt's chaſte Dove, <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.2. or as void of any form (Imagery, or Idols of the heart) as the water, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be impregnated with the ſpirit from on high, without firſt ſpilling her blood; or (which is all one, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.4.)
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:34920:18"/>loſing her own life which is therein: nor enter into the moſt holy Manſions this Spirit doth make in the Father's houſe, <hi>John</hi> 14.2. (according as he allays and ſatiates the Father's Fire in the Souls of Men) but by her own blood, like Chriſt, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.12. and by offering herſelf wholly, as that Sacrifice which was to be wholly burned, or conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by Fire, <hi>Levit.</hi> 1.9. Judgment ſaith, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.17. begins at the Houſe of God, that is, at the Believers. By Fire, and by his Sword, the Lord will plead with all fleſh; and <hi>the ſlain of the Lord,</hi> who are the choſen of God, ſhall not be few, but <hi>many, Iſa.</hi> 66.16.</p>
            <p>To conclude, as in Nature Life begins in the Fire, and is fully perfected in the Light, as I ſaid; all taking the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of its Life, or of Motion, from Heat by Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the Light itſelf (which is Life, or the perfection of Life) coming out of the Fire, and ſubſiſting no where one moment without Fire; ſo in Divine Things alſo; For <hi>Deus eſt ubique ſemper ſibi ſimilis;</hi> God acts in all things alike: Our Divine or New Life muſt begin at the Fire, and we muſt return unto the Rock from which we were hewed, and whence all things take their Birth and Motion, and Duration. Our Life muſt take from thence its firſt Principle of Motion, (which Motion is to be quell'd again, by pouring water abundantly upon it) that being kindled anew by ſome extraordinary ſpark of Grace, which (like Leaven added to Meal or Liquors, ſets them in Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.31, 33.) it may ferment, or be ſet in a hot burning Fever, till it hath purged itſelf of its filth; or of its Droſs, as doth refined Silver or Gold upon the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel; and does thereby become pure and capable to abide with the devouring Fire, or live for ever with God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.14. For, as a Cordial given to a Patient, who labours un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſome great Infection that hath invaded his Life, ſets
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:34920:19"/>him firſt in a great heat, or hot Fit, till Life helped by the ſtrength of the Phyſick, and by ſome drink given him at that time that comforts him, overcomes its Enemy, and drives it away by ſweat: So this Spark ſetting the Soul on Fire for a good while, brings a hot Fit upon it, and burns it ſo, that it longs after nothing but Moiſture, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.24. which, as ſoon as it is <hi>ſent</hi> to it by the Refreſher, it draws ſo vehemently, that it falls into that ſtate, which in a Chymical ſenſe may be properly called <hi>Deliquium ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae,</hi> that is, the Soul giving or melting into water: or elſe <hi>drinking in the way,</hi> Pſal. 110 7. of the ſame <hi>Brook</hi> as Chriſt did, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.23. that is, of an abſolute Reſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to God's Will, <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.39, 42. and receiving from this <hi>Cup</hi> ſome comfort and refreſhment; it is enabled to ſwear, or to maſter and expel the ſtrange Fire of thoſe Luſts, which by infecting of it, had been the occaſion of this preternatural Burning or Fermentation; and to dip itſelf at laſt into a Flood of water, whereof the Flood of <hi>Noah</hi> (ſaith <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 3.21.) was a Figure; and thus to be baptized with the ſame Baptiſm as Chriſt was Hence, Phyſicians, learn to give your Patients Drink, when they are in a hot burning Fever. And you, Phyſicians of Souls, help to ſet yours in this Life into a hot burning Fit; and for Drink, leave them to Chriſt, for you cannot give it them, till you have got ſome your ſelves.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> have a Tradition, that the <hi>Meſſiah's</hi> days will be a time of Weeping, Faſting, and Tribulation: yet, like our Lip-Chriſtians, who crack of the Law of Grace, and underſtand it no more than the Wife of <hi>Zebedee,</hi> Mat. 20.20. they look for Eaſe in thoſe days: whereas Eaſe is not the way leading to Eternal Life, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.13. In this world, ſaith Chriſt to them, who do really learn of him, you ſhall have Tribulation, <hi>John</hi> 16.33. And <hi>verily you ſhall weep and lament,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ver.</hi> 20, 21, 22. <hi>to all,</hi> Mark 13.22.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:34920:19"/>
               <hi>But the world ſhall rejoice, and ye ſhall be ſorrowful as a woman in travail: but I'll ſee you again, and your heart ſhall rejoice,</hi> becauſe you are, by this Birth, deliver'd as a tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Woman of a new Creature. For <hi>by much Tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion we get into God's Kingdom,</hi> Acts 14.22. the entrance into Life being <hi>through this narrow gate:</hi> which, as it is known but to very few, but few go through, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.14. Yet God would have us to be ſaved, by going through it out of the Houſe of Bondage, the feveriſh and oppreſſive Infection of our Sins: as did the old <hi>Iſrael,</hi> our Type, out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> called the Iron Furnace, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.20. which burns the fierceſt of all: and paſſing through the Red Sea; and then living, as he did, in the Deſart 40 years; that is, as having no hope of any thing in the world all the time of our Life, (40 Years being the time of moſt Mens Life in this world) and being for 40 days tempted with <hi>Moſes</hi> and Chriſt in the Deſart of this world, with Hunger, Thirſt, Want, Contempt, and Sickneſs, and Miſery, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the 40 days of Plenty, Glory, Pleaſures, wherein <hi>Adam</hi> was tempted in the Garden of <hi>Eden:</hi> For ſo long he was tempted, by the deſire he had to have the world at his Will, and to diſpoſe of it independently from God: and ſo long he was courted by the world (which would have him for its own) before he fell. For thô he was in the world, yet he was not of the world, and he lived out of it in quite another principle or ſtate, <hi>viz.</hi> in that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven wherein the Son of Man was, thô he was come down from thence, <hi>John</hi> 3.33. as yet the love of the world had not captivated him. And wo be to him, that dies, with <hi>Adam,</hi> in thoſe pleaſures, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.6. or in the Wilderneſs (the dry place which Chriſt ſpeaks of, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.43.) with the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> before the 40 days of Temptation are ended, <hi>chap.</hi> 24.48. Therefore all Chriſtians ſhould be made acquainted with theſe things, and their Watchmen,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:34920:20"/>ſaith <hi>Joel</hi> 2.1. ſhould blow the Trumpet aloud, and ſound an Alarm to them (for note, this is to be done in the Lord's holy Mountain, the Church; amongſt the Faithful, and not amongſt the Heathen) to warn them of that Fire and Sword which the Lord pleads with, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33. and which is the terrible and gloomy day of the Lord. But, I doubt, I am <hi>Vox clamantis in deſerto:</hi> that is, where no body hears: For, <hi>O Lord, who is the man that believes our report? and to whom hath the arm of the Lord been revealed?</hi> John 12.38. <hi>There is none that ſtirreth up himſelf to take hold of thee,</hi> Iſa. 64.7. However God is over all things; and when we water and plant, he may give encreaſe; and he hath not lighted my Candle for me to hide or keep it under my Bed, but to make it ſhine as far as I can to others: which is, I hope, warrant enough for me to write; without any further Licence, or Ordination.</p>
            <p>See what <hi>Thomas à Kempis,</hi> and many other wiſe Men have left us in writing, of the way to Happineſs, and of the neceſſity of entring into the Life, Death, and Sufferings of Chriſt: For becauſe theſe things be true, (I mean, what I ſaid of the Baptiſm of Fire, and of the Birth of Water) all wiſe Men, who always know and juſtifie Truth, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.35. own them; and have often declared and taught them: But as there is a variety of Gifts, and of Adminiſtrations, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.4, 5. they have differently alſo expreſſed the ſame. <hi>Jamblichus</hi> of Myſteries: <hi>Haec utique ſit tibi ad foelicitatem via. Conſider are decet quà praecipue ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione ſolvi poſſis à vinculis quibus anima circa formas at que ſpecies mundi contemperatur. Eſt autem ſolutio nulla praeter ipſam Dei cognitionem. Idea namque foelicitatis eſt ipſum cognoſcere Bonum: quemadmodum eſt &amp; Idea malorum ipſa quidem bonorum oblivio, quae eſt deceptio inſeparabilis à cadu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co; à principiis enim cadens at que repulſa ſe ipſam projicit ad
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:34920:20"/>corporalem ideam dimetiendam: à qua corporali Idea ſolvi debes, ut contemplationi &amp; cognitioni Dei rurſus jungaris. Plato</hi> calls this (I me an this ſtate of Water, whereby we become void of the Forms (Idea's) of outward things) <hi>Converſio animae humanae in ſeipſam;</hi> the Soul converting from things without it into itſelf. Great <hi>Hermes,</hi> with <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> Cant. 5.2. <hi>Ob dormitio mentis à corporis ſenſibus:</hi> A ſleeping of the Body, whil'ſt our Soul is waking. I ſleep, but my heart is awake, (like <hi>Balaam</hi>'s eyes, that were open all the while his Body was in a trance, <hi>Numb.</hi> 24.4.) and burning beſides, like that of the two Diſciples of Chriſt in their way to <hi>Emmaus,</hi> Luke 24.32. The <hi>Popiſh</hi> Saints call the ſame the internal way to God, and inward Recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection: of which <hi>Molina</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi> hath lately ſaid enough to ſet the Prieſts againſt him, who cannot abide to hear of dying and ſuffering: but only of that which makes <hi>their heart glad,</hi> (Judg. 18.20.) a Fat Living. The whole Sum of Religion <hi>is for man to keep himſelf unſpotted from world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things,</hi> or from the Love of the World, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.27. for in this conſiſts the Love of God, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.24. and the Love of God, with that of our Neighbour, is the great Commandment, and the Law, and the Prophets. A great Proteſtant Divine, Famous both for Piety and Learning, Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> in anſwer to a Queſtion about Sanctification which one made, expreſſeth thus this Abſtraction from the World, and this dying by Fire. <hi>I muſt tell you,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>we do not well underſtand what is Sanctification, or the New Creature, which God formeth by his own Spirit in every Soul which be regenerates of</hi> water: <hi>For it is no leſs than for a Man to be brought to an entire reſignation of his will to the Will of God, and to live in the offering up of his Soul as a whole Burnt-offering, like Chriſt, to God the Father. And how little are many of thoſe who profeſs Chriſtianity, experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally acquainted with this work in their Souls?</hi> Nay, and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionally
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:34920:21"/>too, I add; the Proteſtants knowing little more of this, I mean of the way to become a new Creature, than what they call Repentance.</p>
            <p>Which Word yet, being taken in its right and genuine ſenſe, ſiguifies more than what they ſeem to underſtand by it; that is, more than any ſorrow for Sin, and ſetting upon mending, amounts to: For what is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>? Is it either <hi>Proteſtant</hi> or <hi>Catholick</hi> Repentance? No ſurely, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is neither laſhing your backs, nor grieving two or three hours: But it is the amendment itſelf duly performed: it is a Reſipiſcence, which is no leſs in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> than a Fool and a Knave, becoming, at the ſame time, both a wiſe and a good Man; and a change, or converſion from one ſtate or quality, <hi>viz.</hi> the Nature of a Beaſt, to the moſt oppoſite ſtate, to wit, the Divine Nature, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. or at leaſt that of Angels, <hi>Luke</hi> 20.36. Which Chriſtians flatter themſelves in vain to attain unto by their common Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: for there needs a hard ſtriving; a man muſt be violent to take God's Kingdom by Force: And it can never be done, without paſſing the great Gulph of God's Vengeance and Wrath threatned, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.17. <hi>Luke</hi> 16.26.- 21.22. And thô <hi>Peter</hi> in the <hi>Acts,</hi> 2.38-3.19. mentions only the Baptiſm of Water and Repentance, as the things neceſſary to obtain the Holy Ghoſt, that makes Man a New Creature: yet in his <hi>Firſt Epiſtle,</hi> ſpeaking of another thing not ſtrange to the Believers, to wit, <hi>the Firy Tryal,</hi> he ſhews thereby, that they go through ſome other thing than that which he calls there Repentance: or that the word <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> with the word, <hi>Be Converted</hi> added to it in that place, includes the <hi>Firy Tryal;</hi> which he would not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion there, becauſe he ſpake before a mixt Aſſembly of People; and it being one of thoſe many things Chriſt (who forbids to caſt Pearls before Swine) would not yet
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:34920:21"/>ſay to the World (<hi>John</hi> 16.12.) (that cannot favor the things of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. or more than <hi>Peter,</hi> endure to hear of dying, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.22, 23.) he would not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it them, but left to the Holy Ghoſt the Revelation thereof to them that were not without God's Kingdom, as the World is, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.11. But becauſe it is God's Will that <hi>all men ſhould be ſaved,</hi> by opening of their blind eyes, and <hi>by co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming</hi> at the laſt to the <hi>knowledg of the Truth,</hi> and the harveſt is grown ripe, as it appears from the <hi>French</hi> Prophets and their Propheſies; I think it is high time for them that make mention of the Lord, not to keep ſilence, but to tell it pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly, and found an Alarm of it. But whether <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> comprehends this thing or no, ſure it is, that we muſt dye, before we live again, or come to another life; and the death of the Body doth bring no life to the Soul: therefore the Soul is to die: and as the eternal Soul cannot corrupt or decay, it is not obnoxious to ſuch diſſolution or death as the Body is; and ſo the death of the Soul can be no cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption or diſſolution of it, but a continual dying, agony, ſtrugling with death, or ſuch an anguiſhing pain as we may conceive a Man feels when he is a dying. And this Fight, or Agony muſt be, as I have ſaid, with Burning, or with Fire: <hi>For every battel of men is with a confuſed noiſe, and garments rolled in blood; but this ſhall be with burning, and with fewel of fire,</hi> Iſa. 9.5. To which he adds, <hi>ver.</hi> 6. to ſhew us that this precedes the Baptiſm, or the New Birth of Water; the Water-like <hi>Child is born, the Son</hi> of Man is formed in the Virgin Soul of Man, and grows there, till he becomes the <hi>wonderful mighty God,</hi> and <hi>the Prince of Peace</hi> to him. Under the Law, all thoſe things that could abide the Fire, were purified by Fire; and thoſe that could not bear it, were purified with Water; to ſhew us what was to be the true cleanſing of the Soul; whil'ſt as yet, in this Body of Fleſh, under the Goſpel. And many of the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:34920:22"/>Fathers, to ſhew that this is no new Doctrine, ſpeak at the ſame rate: Amongſt whom <hi>Ambroſius,</hi> and <hi>Origen,</hi> on the firſt <hi>Chapter</hi> of <hi>Leviticus,</hi> and <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36. have left us theſe Paſſages: <hi>Chriſtus,</hi> faith <hi>Ambroſius, baptizat in Spiritu ſancto &amp; igne, qui Spiritus ſancti typus &amp; imago eſt, &amp; qui, ignis inſtar, cor &amp; animam fidelium inflammat, ut probet eos, ſecundum Apoſtolum,</hi> 1 Cor. 3. <hi>Nam neceſſe eſt at hoc examen perficiatur apud omnes qui redibunt in Paradiſum. Oportet nos omnes,</hi> faith <hi>Origen, at que Paulum &amp; Petrum,</hi> (who ſaith, I <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.17. that the <hi>time was come,</hi> (ſince the Agony of Chriſt) <hi>that</hi> the Saints were to be tried, and that this firy Tryal (which he calleth their <hi>judgment</hi>) <hi>muſt begin firſt at</hi> them, <hi>and at the</hi> whole <hi>houſe of God</hi>) <hi>intrare in talem purgatorium ignem: ſed omnes non eodem modo ac illi tranſibunt: nam non omnes purgantur per ignem qui exit de Altari, qui eſt ignis Domini: nam ignis qui eſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Altare (Altare autem eſt Chriſtus qui mittit nobis ignem Spiritus Sancti) non eſt ignis Domini; ſed ignis peregrinus in peccatorum cruciatum deſtinatus, qui nunquam extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; ut vermis qui rodit eos nunquam moritur: Nam poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam anima per multitudinem malefactorum in ſe cumulavit abundantiam peccatorum; iſta congregatio malorum cum tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore fermentat, &amp; à poena &amp; ſupplicio interno flammam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipit; ſicuti corpus febrem ab exceſſu gulae, aut aliarum ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluitatum; cum in memorian revocare, &amp; malefactorum hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoriam retexere incipiet: quae ipſi perpetuus ſtimulus erunt ad torquendum: ſui ipſius accuſatrix erit, &amp; teſtimonium da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit contra ſemet ipſam, ut Apoſtolus, inquit ad</hi> Rom 2. <hi>inter ſe invicem accuſantibus, aut etiam defendentibus cogitationi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, in die quâ judicabit Dominus occulta hominum. Sed Jeremias,</hi> cap. 25. <hi>Loquitur depotione irae Dei quae effundetur, &amp; quicunque de illa bibere non volet, non purificabitur. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde diſcimus, inquit, quod irae Dei effuſio in corda</hi> (quam, amoris Dei effuſio ſequitur, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.5.) <hi>facit ad purgationem ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marum.</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:34920:22"/>Haec ille. Whence we learn, that the Fire of God's wrath in the Soul, is both the Death of the Soul, or the Hell of the Wicked; and the Purgatory of the Souls of the Faithful; of which he that will not drink, ſhall never be purified, and ſo ſhall never enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.14-13.11: and that this Firy Tryal is not ſo violent in ſome, to wit, that have led a holy Life before it, as in others that have led an ungodly, ſinful Life, whoſe multitude of ſins kindle a greater Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation. Out of this the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that knows but the dead Letter of the Chriſtian Myſteries; and hath depraved them, to make a ſordid gain of them, hath drawn her Purgatory. And theſe things ſuffice, to prove that this dying by Fire, and this new Birth of Water, are the true and onely way, or <hi>quomodo</hi> of Wiſdom; that is, how to obtain the Spirit that gives Wiſdom: without which, all the ſtudy for Knowledge is but in vain: as they that ſee in ſeeing may find to be true in moſt of the learned at the Schools: who never find any thing beſides the Opinion they have at firſt received, thô it be never ſo Falſe; whereas a true Learned man, <hi>brings forth daily out of his</hi> ever-ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Well or <hi>Stock</hi> of Wiſdom, <hi>things new and old,</hi> Matth. 13.52: and who, not only know not that theſe things are the true and direct way to Wiſdom, but preferring their Darkneſs to Light, will not juſtifie or own this truth when told them; and will keep for all this ſucking the dry, empty Breaſts of their old <hi>Alma Mater,</hi> (ſo they call <hi>Academies</hi>) and <hi>filling</hi> thus more and more, as <hi>Eliphaz</hi> ſaith in <hi>Job</hi> 15.2. <hi>their Bellies with the Eaſt wind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here I would not be underſtood, as if I meant that there is no Knowledge at all of Natural Things, without this Death and this Birth: For <hi>ſurely there is a place for Gold, a vein for Silver, Iron and Braſs,</hi> by Knowledge got
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:34920:23"/>without ſuch means as theſe, <hi>are molten out of their Oar, Job</hi> 28.1, 2. That is, an implicit Knowledge, in part, may be had from others in many things; <hi>But where ſhall Wiſdom be found? It is not to be found in the Land of the Living. ver.</hi> 12, 13. Now Wiſdom, as I ſaid, is not a Knowledge in part, and of one part of the World, Enthuſiaſtically inſpired in our minds; For in the caſe of Knowledge, which is a ſight of all the true Cauſes concurring in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of ſuch Effect or <hi>Phoenomenon,</hi> as is become the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of a Man's Meditation, there can be no ſuch thing: But it is a Light ſhining or breaking out in the Mind, which, like a ſlaſh of Lightning, makes all thoſe things manifeſt that we could not ſee before, though we were juſt upon them, by reaſon of our ſtanding in the dark with them: ſo that we can thereby ſee and perceive what things they are; nay, read in them, and through them, by their outward ſignature, <hi>per quid &amp; quomodo,</hi> that is, in what manner and by what, they become ſuch; provided we ſet upon the Contemplation of them. For, as the Flaſh makes not Men ſee what is out of their ſight, or what they look not upon, thô it ſhines through, and gives light over the whole Hemiſphere: So, thô the light of Wiſdom doth make all things manifeſt, and expoſe to our View the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Cauſes of Things, yet it will not in this Life make us underſtand a Thing which we do not think upon; and prompt us, on a ſudden, with the full Knowledge of that which, perhaps, we never heard and conſider'd of before; without we take it into ſerious conſideration, and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate upon it, like <hi>Iſaac,</hi> by our ſelves, <hi>Gen.</hi> 24.63. Albeit, after this Life, when Things ſhall be deliver'd from their Opacous Body, (the Bondage of Corruption, which, by the Fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> they have been ſubjected to, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.20) into the glorious liberty of God's Children, <hi>ver.</hi> 21. (a through ſhining, tranſparent Body, which Men may ſee
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:34920:23"/>through, and that ſtops the ſight no more) we ſhall ſee all at one ſight, and know every thing at firſt ſight, as we know one whom we are acquainted with, when we meet him Face to Face, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12. So that a brown ſtudy, ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and examining, <hi>riſing early, and watching</hi> at the Poſts of Wiſdom's doors, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.17, 34. is alſo neceſſary in this Life to get Wiſdom. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>It will lead you in the way,</hi> John 16.13. implies, that a Man muſt walk to come to his Journies end, to wit, the Knowledge of Truth. But, thô he ſhould walk never ſo long, and hit the right way, and light upon Truth by Chance; yet ſo long as he is blind, and beſides ſtands in the dark, he can by no means ſee it, and diſcern, when he ſees it, that it is what he looks for: and as he found it by chance, he goes from it, loſeth it as eaſie as he found it, and keeps <hi>ſtill ſeeking after, and yet never coming to any knowledge of it,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.7. For <hi>until it pleaſeth God to reveal his light in man,</hi> Gal. 1.15, 16. or to give him <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.20. a diſcerning Faculty, no Body can juſtify, or diſcern Truth, from Error and Falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and Opinion. Witneſs <hi>Paul,</hi> who though he was brought up in all the Learning of the <hi>Jews</hi> with <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> and was doubtleſs acquainted with that which the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians taught, at leaſt wherein they differ'd from the Doctrine of the <hi>Jews,</hi> yet he underſtood it not, (for he perſecuted them, and that out of Ignorance, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13.) till he received the Truth <hi>by the Revelation of Chriſt,</hi> as he owns himſelf, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.12. And no more do the Chriſtians of this Age underſtand it: whence every Sect of them ſticks no leſs than the <hi>Turks</hi> and the <hi>Jews</hi> to their own way; (thô all but one, muſt be falſe;) and have a ſtrong preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice againſt all other Parties: Or, if their Eye is ſo ſingle as to liſten to others, they are toſſed to and fro <hi>by every wind of Doctrine,</hi> which ſome cunning Sophiſter, who is reputed Learned amongſt thoſe of his Party, maketh ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:34920:24"/>plauſible: being as much uncertain what to believe of either this new or their old Doctrine, as the <hi>Samaritan</hi> Woman was, when ſhe ſaid, <hi>Sir, Our Fathers worſhipped in this place, but you ſay that</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>is the place,</hi> Joh 4.19. that is as much as to ſay, Which muſt I now believe, yours, or our Opinion? For Believing depends upon the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding: <hi>Intelligere,</hi> ſaith one, being <hi>Ipſum credere:</hi> the underſtanding of Things being the Belief itſelf; and the Belief or the Faith being an Underſtanding enlightned, <hi>an evidence of things</hi> to the Intellect, which are not ſeen by the Eye, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.1. And this believing of Things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſight of them, becauſe we underſtand them; as it conſtitutes a Man's bleſſed ſtate or happineſs: <hi>For bleſſed is he that hath not ſeen, and yet believeth,</hi> John 20.29. So it makes up the firſt part of Wiſdom or Salvation, as is ſeen in the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>Page,</hi> by Wiſdom's Definition: Nay, ſuch Faith as this is, is called Wiſdom itſelf: <hi>For this ſhall be your Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in the ſight of the Nations,</hi> Deut. 4.6. meaning to do and perform thoſe Precepts we underſtand to be good for us to keep; Faith, like Wiſdom, being not perfected, but in the Act. Therefore a Man muſt be made ſeeing and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; his Eyes muſt be enlightned; and the Light muſt ſhine into the thick Darkneſs he ſtands in, before he can diſcern Truth from Opinion, and believe. And (to come to the Thing I here chiefly aim at) as the Further he goes on, when he is in the right way, the Nearer alſo he draws towards his ſaid Journies end; ſo the more a Man goes on in the right way to Wiſdom, that is, in the ſaid dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Regeneration, the more he is made ſeeing, and the nearer he comes to the bright Crown of Wiſdom: And if he can go thorow the whole courſe of this dying and Regeneration, he may obtain the whole Prize; even the cloſed Crown of Wiſdom, laid up for ſuch, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. For as there be ſeveral Manſions in the Father's houſe, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.2.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:34920:24"/>that is, ſeveral degrees of Wiſdom, and of that which gives Wiſdom (the Holy Ghoſt) in the ſtate of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: So there be ſeveral ſteps and degrees of the ſaid Death and Regeneration: all which if a Man go through, and overcomes to the laſt of them, or the ſeventh time, he ſhall even ſit on Thrones, <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.28. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.2. and ſhine forth as the Sun doth, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.3. <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.43. or be ſill'd, like St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> Acts 6.15-7.55. with the full Light of Wiſdom. But if he ſtops any where at any of thoſe degrees, he ſhall reach to no higher proportion of Light than what doth anſwer to that degree or ſtep which he did ſtop at, and ſhall have but a degree of Knowledge accordingly: nay, and no new Light at all, if he go up none of them. And in caſe he overcome but the firſt ſtep, and ſtop there, he ſhall get but ſuch glimpſe of Light, as will prove to him but an <hi>Ignis Fatuus,</hi> to lead him out of the way: For it will only make him capable <hi>to try others: Rev.</hi> 2.2. And therefore to deſpiſe them, when he finds their Ignorance. And thereby make him the Man meant by the proud <hi>Phariſee,</hi> who falls upon the Shoulders and Vices of other People; or elſe upon nothing but Diſputes about Opinions, inſtead of weeping over himſelf like the <hi>Publican.</hi> Which is the Caſe of our Half-Enlightned Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. Whom Princes cannot ſuffer; becauſe, as they ſee clearer than down-right ignorant People, ſuch as the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> is, they are more apt, than She is, to find Fault with the Conduct and Government of their Prince; and being never a whit the better, or the meeker for this new encreaſe of Light, they become his Cenſurers, and ſo very uneaſie, if not dangerous to him, that he is always ſtriving to remove and ſuppreſs them, or to bring them again to their former Ignorance: which occaſions Diſquiet and Diſcontent on both ſides. But againſt this great Evil, there is a ſure Remedy, which becauſe it is the beſt and the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:34920:25"/>chiefeſt in its kind, none of the State Phyſicians know more of it, than our ordinary Phyſicians do of the <hi>Great Elixir,</hi> or <hi>Arcanum</hi> in Phyſick. Therefore learn of me, Princes, the beſt Rule of Politicks. If you will Reign quietly with Content and Happineſs, you muſt help the Blind to ſee, and the Pur-blind, and Blear-ey'd, to true Illumination: And (ſeeking the Kingdom of God, which is in the Light, <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſ.</hi> 1.12.) make your Subjects Prieſts to God, bring them from their half-witted ſtate of Illumination, to the perfect Noon-day, or the full Light of Wiſdom: by diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenancing all that which may keep them back from the Light and Knowledge which conſtitutes their Prieſthood, <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.7. And by encouraging the ſaid Mortification, and the New Birth of Water, Righteouſneſs, and Holineſs, For then, as the firſt degree of them doth procure no more but that mean degree of Light which ſerves but to make Men proud; ſo the higheſt degree of this Regeneration will procure ſo much of Light, as will make them all, like Chriſt, lowly, meek, and paciſick: and ſo will ſecure the Peace of your Kingdom for ever. For then they will <hi>be ſubject to you for the Oath of God,</hi> Eccleſ. 8.2. Rom. 13.2. And becauſe the Kingdom of God, which they will then ſeek, and not meddle or make with yours therefore, is not of this world. <hi>Foelices Regiones ubi ſapientes regnant, &amp; ubi Populi ipſi philoſophantur!</hi> But unlucky Politicks, to go about (as thoſe do, who promote the ignorant, blind way of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſo oppoſe God's Kingdom) to ſave and keep your Kingdom, by thwarting his Intereſt, and diſobliging of him, <hi>by the Graco of whom alone</hi> you own to have received it, and hope to be maintained and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued therein! The way to keep your Kingdom, is the ſame as to keep Life; that is, by loſing of it, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.25. or by ſacrificing it daily to the Will of God; ſeeking the Will, the Kingdom, and the Intereſt of God, and ſtriving
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:34920:25"/>to promote it above all your Intereſt throughout all your Dominions. When <hi>David</hi> ſought the Kingdom of God, and not his own Ends, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.22. his Kingdom was for ever eſtabliſhed unto him, <hi>chap.</hi> 7.16. Whereas <hi>Saul</hi> loſt his Kingdom by ſeeking his own Honour, and ſtriving to preſerve it without regard to God's Will, 1 <hi>Sam</hi> 13.13, 14- 15.28, 30. And at laſt his great Head piece, inſtead of the Majeſty and Honour he ſought after, got him but an Aſſes head, <hi>chap.</hi> 16.14. remembring his men no more, <hi>chap.</hi> 17.58. thô before he loved them, and was by them diverted, <hi>chap.</hi> 16.21. Whereas when he went to work without any policy, ſought after Aſſes only, he got a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom beſides, and Honour, and Majeſty: and he might have ſecur'd it to him, and his for ever, by uſing the ſame method as he did when he got it; that is, by ſeeking ſtill after his Fathers Aſſes, or uſing an Aſinine, and a Dove-like Induſtry and Prudence, <hi>Math</hi> 10.16. without cunning: or (as one that is employed by another in ſeeking) by being always ready to give him what he hath found; and ſo to yield up to God, who is the Father of Kings, and by whom they are ſet up in this World to do his Work, all their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Power, Glory, and their Life itſelf. But the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way, which is called in Scripture the way of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> is ſo natural to Kings, that of the 40 Kings who Reigned after <hi>David</hi> over the two Kingdoms of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> we find but One in Seven avoided falling in it. And, <hi>in tempore ſuo dicetur Iſraeli,</hi> in its time it ſhall be told the true <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, how many ſuch Kings are found in the Chronicles of <hi>England,</hi> Numb. 23.23. For we are not without hope that His preſent Majeſty will make one of that Number; which God, who turneth the Hearts of Princes as He pleaſeth, grant Him in his great Mercy: or elſe there is but one Law, <hi>Eſth.</hi> 4.11. the Fate of <hi>Jeroboam</hi> follows <hi>Jeroboam</hi>'s way, for ſurely his Hiſtory was not
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:34920:26"/>written in vain. <hi>But in vain is ſalvation hoped for from hills of Gold, and from numerous Armies,</hi> ſee <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.23. and my Dedicatory Epiſtle to the late King, and Sir <hi>Walter Raw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leigh</hi>'s Preface to his Hiſtory; where I have read theſe words: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na dies, hora, momentum, evertendis dominationibus ſufficit, quae adamantinis videbantur radicibus eſſe firmatae.</hi> What he that doth not ſee now to be true, is more than blind, or hath been in a deep Sleep ever ſince <hi>October</hi> laſt.</p>
            <p>But, to conclude this Diſcourſe; as by a thorow dying comes the full light of Wiſdom, ſo without dying in part, or ſome ſuch degree of true Mortification, as is the pricking of heart, or contrition, in the <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37. (which the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern <hi>French</hi> Prophets are gone through, as it appears by their printed Relation) there is not any part of Wiſdom to be lookt for; though a Man ſhould be taught of all the Learned in the World: but ſcraps of Learning enough; and the vain deceit, whereof <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.8. to wit, Logical Sophiſms. Which is all I hereby underſtood, and nothing elſe.</p>
            <p>The Application of this to <hi>England,</hi> is not ſo hard to do as the thing it ſelf. That which I make of it is this, to wit, this Doctrine muſt be either true or falſe. If falſe, then God's Word is falſe; for theſe things are <hi>verbatim,</hi> or almoſt <hi>verbatim</hi> contained in the Scriptures; this being but a kind of <hi>Paraphraſis</hi> upon it: And Nature itſelf is falſe; that is, not ſuch as it is; for it works no other way in the Regeneration and Generation of Things than what I have deſcrib'd: Only, as natural Things, ſuch as Herbs and Minerals, never fell from their Principle, that is, the ſame kind of Life they originally had, to another worſe Principle, or kind of Life and Being than their own, as <hi>Adam</hi> did, thô they ſell with him under the bondage of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:34920:26"/>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.21. (for neither the Corruption nor Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation of things, changeth their Kind or <hi>Genus</hi>) but live ſtill of the ſame Life, and keep in the ſame Principle as they liv'd in from the firſt; that is, in the Principle and Life of this outward World: ſo, they go not out of it into another new kind of Life, when they are by Art purified and exalted) it may be abuſively called Regenerated) and begin not a new Life, but only have the old one made bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and reformed; and therefore they need not go again thrô the ſierce Fire (where all things generally begin their Life, and from whence they take the firſt riſe of their Life, or their Original) as the Soul of Man muſt do, (by reaſon that, as it fell from a whole Principle, or kind of Being, to another, that is, from the Divine Life in the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of the Light, to this preſent beaſtly Life in the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of this World; it is not enough for it to have the old one mended; it muſt begin a new one, and paſs from that it fell to, to that kind which it fell from: whence Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance implies more than a bare Reformation, and mending of the old Life; for, to tell the truth of it, it is a new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.10. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.24.) But they may be more fitly purified and exalted by frequent Inhumations and Dippings in the water; without perceptible heat; which in the birth of Water cannot but be offenſive. For thô the <hi>Chymiſts</hi> calcine or burn their things with Fire, yet the Wiſemen ever did burn or calcine with Water: and they cry, <hi>tere, tere; &amp; imbibe, imbibe.</hi> But when this outward Principle, the World, ſhall be totally deliver'd from the Bondage and Curſe of its Corruption, (the denſity, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pactneſs, and hardneſs of its Body) into the glorious li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of God's Children, (a thin tranſparent Body) and ſo ſhall paſs from this kind of Being to a new one, then it ſhall again go thrô the fierceneſs of the Fire; then <hi>the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhall melt with fervent heat,</hi> ſaith <hi>Peter,</hi> 2.3, 10. and <hi>the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:34920:27"/>Earth ſhall be burnt up,</hi> and ſhall be, with the waters, redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced again into a glorious Quinteſſence, <hi>on which the ranſomed of the Lord ſhall ſtand with ſongs, and with joy upon their heads,</hi> Rev. 15.2. Iſa. 35.10. Matth. 5.5.</p>
            <q>[As there are three diſtinct kinds of Lives (as, I have ſaid already in the Twelfth Page) all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted things live of, and are, as by ſo many <hi>Claſſes,</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed by, and comprehended under, as ſo many <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> under their <hi>Genus</hi> or Kind; ſo there be three ſeveral Principles, according to ſome; which give all created things their ſpeciſick Form of Life, and determinate all thoſe which are within their <hi>Claſſis,</hi> after their own Property. And they may well be called Principles, ſo long as all things have their Life in and from them; and ſo long as theſe three Lives are the Original Being or State, things fell in, or betook themſelves unto from their firſt Original. The firſt is the Fire Life, or the Principle of Fire; common to all living things, for aſmuch as they all take from them the Original and the firſt Riſe of their Life; but proper to the Devils, and the damned Souls only: The ſecond is the Divine Life, or Principle of the Light, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Angels, and Men were perfected, and made good, <hi>Gen. 1.31.</hi> but, from which both of them fell, <hi>Jud. ver. 6.</hi> and is proper only to the confirmed Angels, and the Souls of the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. The third is this outward Life, or the Principle of this World, where all things live in the Air of the Spirit which comes down from the Heavens into it: and is proper to the Beaſts, and to the preſent Body of Man, and to all thoſe things which live in it and from it; but became accidental to Man, by reaſon that he fell into it, as was ſaid. And the firſt is aſcribed to God the Father of Life, as being but a burning, ſharp, fierce, and obſcure Fire, without the Light of the Son: The ſecond to God the Son, as being the Light of Life, that ſweetneth and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:34920:27"/>perfects it: and the third and laſt of them to God the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, as being the Conveyer and the Refreſher of Life, that brings Life, and preſerves it; and that proceeds, like the Air, from the Fire, and the Light of the Father and the Son.]</q>
            <p>For, to enlarge upon this, when God created the world, or (to make the word <hi>Create</hi> ſomewhat more intelligible) did make himſelf manifeſt, he manifeſted himſelf ſuch as he is in himſelf; that is, by a Trinity in Unity, Fire, Light, and Spirit, in one Being. Therefore he make three Spring Heads, or Prineiples of all Things, three Throne-Angels with their Worlds. <hi>Michael,</hi> the mighty ſtrong Prince, after the fierce Nature and Property of Fire: <hi>Lucifer,</hi> the lovely, the bright, and moſt glorious Prince, after the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant nature and property of the Light: and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riel,</hi> the Well-doer, or the Introducer and Conveyer of the Light, or of all the pleaſantneſs and good that comes from the Light, after the beneficent Nature of the Holy Ghoſt: each one a diſtinct Principle, and all the three together ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king up one Unity, or total Being, like God; to wit, the inviſible and intelligible World; and comprehending in them the whole Creation of God; and each of them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of Fire, Light, and Spirit. For, as the end of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>alias</hi> of the Naſciture (Manifeſtation) of God, was to communicate his <hi>Summum Bonum</hi> (Himſelf) to all created Beings, his Will and Purpoſe was not that the Principle of Fire, Evil, ſhould predominate, and ſubſiſt in any thing by itſelf without the Light, but that the Light ſhould take place, and the Angels with their Worlds ſhould become ſuch as God is, a moſt joyful Being, and a pleaſant Paradiſe. Therefore, thô God created each in a diſtinct Principle, yet he made each of them; that is <hi>Michael,</hi> as well as <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riel</hi> and <hi>Lucifer,</hi> to conſiſt of thoſe three things; and to paſs immediately from the Fire to the Light; and to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:34920:28"/>ſend forth or exhale (like the Sun) out of himſelf a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit into his Sphere, to vivify, and to ſeed and ſuſtent it all over. Upon which, ſaith <hi>Triſmegiſt, Omnia lux fuerunt, vel in lumen converſa, jucundum &amp; ſuave nimium Spectacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum!</hi> For God is light, and in him there is no darkneſs at all, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.5. And all things had for ever continued in this ſame ſtate, if <hi>Lucifer,</hi> who being the moſt glorious of the three, had not admired himſelf, and inſtead of loving and admiring God for it, and of ſeeking God's Kingdom and Glory more than his own, fall'n in love with his own ſelf; whence he (as a Man in love doth, by his longing, attract what he loves into himſelf, and <hi>his Soul,</hi> ſaith the Scripture, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.39. doth, as it were, iſſue out, or <hi>go forth</hi> to join with it) drew himſelf into himſelf; and by the aſtringency of his Luſt or Deſire, (for Luſt or Deſire is aſtringent and attractive) filling, or impregnating, and offuſcating himſelf; as one that dotes upon that which he loves, whether it be Man, Woman, Gold or Silver, cannot receive in his mind any other thing but that; his mind runs upon nothing but his beloved treaſure; and is wholly taken up with it; <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.21. he becomes penſive, and as it were overcaſt with a thick Cloud or dark Miſt; ſo he was offuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, and became cloudy and dark; and as the more he luſted and drew, the more and thicker the Clouds did ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and grow, whereby a Heat and Burning was excitated in him, and he was reinflamed; as it doth happen to thoſe who having kept their Luſts a good while under Hatches, break out into the more violent heat and paſſion; and to a wet heap of Hay, Fruits, Flowers, and other things, which are apt to ferment, and to grow hot of themſelves, by reaſon that the Vapor or the Cloud that comes from them, during their Fermentation, being kept within the heap (by the Contiguity and Coherence of its parts, which affords no paſſage or way for Tranſpiration)
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:34920:28"/>grows there thicker and thicker. And withall he ſet his Sphere (which being a thin Matter, was as apt as any Smoke is, to take Flame) on Fire: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Matter thereof (which was very thin and ſubtle) was concocted and hardned, its looſe parts were compacted into a cloſer texture and Conſiſtence than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; and ſome of them were hardned and coagulated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Earth, Stones, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by the ſtrong aſtringency of his ſharp auſtere Fire: as you ſee that, of Water (which is an Air, or rather a thin Vapor condenſed) is made an Ice, and an Oil: the Ice, for want of a heat able to melt or thaw it, is hardned into Chryſtal; the Oil, by due concoction, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a Salt and an Earth; and this Earth, by a ſtrong heat, is hardned into a Brick: and that thus out of the Clouds, by the Fire that breaks out of them, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacts the thin and moſt earthy parts of them, into a hard Lump or Stone, Thunderbolts are produced. By which means <hi>Lucifer</hi>'s Sphere, (which is this viſible World, for he is ſtill Prince of it, <hi>John</hi> 12.31.) and with it all the Concretes, became palpable or tangible: Thus this world was created; a third Principle produced; thus the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Fire came to be creaturely; and thus Evil begun and ſubſiſts now in the world; And <hi>ex inviſibili,</hi> this world was thus made viſible: that is, after the Light was made to ſhine in it again. For until it pleaſed God to reveal his Light therein, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.16. there was nothing but a ſharp, dark, grim, auſtere Face over, and through the whole Deep or Sphere; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbra horrenda mortis;</hi> and, an inflamed Devil, burning very terribly, and furiouſly ſtorming and caſting his firy darts or flames into all its parts, and as far as God himſelf. But then God (whoſe Nature, Will, Power, and Act, is but one and the ſame thing at all times) reſiſting by his Nature, which is the <hi>Summum Bonum,</hi> the oppoſite Will, Nature, and Power of <hi>Lucifer,</hi> made the Light (which
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:34920:29"/>is the end of Nature) to overcome; to thaw this ſtiff frozen World; and to ſpring a ſecond time, even through this Death and Hell, into a new Paradiſe; and glorify'd it again, by caſting out the Prince of this world, <hi>John</hi> 12. 28, 31. into his darkneſs, or dark Fire <hi>for ever,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2 4. becauſe he was the Author of ſuch Fire in Nature, and had changed the <hi>Pulchrum</hi> and the <hi>Bonum</hi> of the Light, the good and the delightſom, into darkneſs and evil; and by deſtroying the Light, had killed God in himſelf. For God is the Light, that is, the good and the bliſs of Life, who, by living in Angels and Men, makes them live happy; and therefore when they kill him, as do all thoſe that put out their Light, that is, fall again when they have been enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.6. he never more lives in them; and they live no more, but die, laying in a continual horror, dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and anguiſh. Thus, as <hi>Lucifer</hi> had been, by re-kindling his Fire, the <hi>Originator,</hi> or the occaſional cauſe of this 3d Principle, the World; ſo, God, by opening again the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Light therein, created and perfected the ſame into a Principle; which was mixt as it is now, that is, did par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of both Principles of good and evil: whereof the Tree of Knowledge in the midſt of the Garden was a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament or, Sign: what no other Tree that grew in the ſame Garden could be, becauſe they ſprung like <hi>Adam,</hi> from the Principle of the Light, which made the Garden to be <hi>Eden,</hi> or a Paradiſe.</p>
            <p>It would not be amiſs to ſhew here,
<list>
                  <item>(1) that <hi>Adam</hi> was created in that Principle, and made a ſecond. Angel in the ſtead of <hi>Lucifer:</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>(2) That he fell from it by luſting and attracting, filling, darkning, enflaming of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, like <hi>Lucifer,</hi> till his own Light grew ſo weak and ſaint that he fell aſleep:</item>
                  <item>(3) That it was this mixt World which he thus luſted after, imagining into, and looking back
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:34920:29"/>into that out of which he was taken, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.7. like <hi>Lot</hi>'s Wife into <hi>Sodom,</hi> inſtead of looking <hi>Eaſtward,</hi> or forwards, towards the light, all the time he was tempted; upon which he fell aſleep.</item>
                  <item>(4) That upon the biting and ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of the Apple, he was ſeized upon, invaded and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected by the Four Elements, which ſtampt, <hi>per contactum,</hi> their mark and badge upon him, as doth the longing Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon the Fruit in her womb, cloathing him over with this rough, hairy, beaſtly, or elementary Body; what they could not have done elſe, having no power at all over him before eating: whereby he became of <hi>Iſoh</hi> (the Divine Man, in the Light) <hi>Adam,</hi> (the dark, cloudy Man) from <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> a Miſt, or a Cloud; not from <hi>Adamah,</hi> the Earth, as our Wiſemen make it; for <hi>Adamah</hi> itſelf is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from <hi>Adam,</hi> as being his <hi>Adamah,</hi> or the thing <hi>Adam</hi> dwelt on. And which elementary Body is cut off from him, never to return, or riſe again, as the Divines teach; becauſe the Elements themſelves, from whence it proceeds, ſhall paſs away for ever, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10: and as it is what kills him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24. and makes him a fallen Man, a Man of Sorrows and Grief; wretched, dark, and cloudy; he muſt be delivered from it, and from its bondage, into the glorious Liberty of God's Children, to be happy, or ſaved. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.13.</item>
                  <item>(5) That <hi>in the cool of the day,</hi> that it, after the fierceneſs of his burning was over, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.8. when he was come to the ſtate, or the new birth of water, he heard God ſpeak, and promiſe to him and to his Children, (to the end God's Will might ſtand and prevail againſt the Gates of Hell, and the Devil's Will) the Light, Chriſt, the third Angel. Who ſhould bring again to him Liſe and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.10. and reſtore this corrupted hard bound World to its former liberty, the clear bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs it enjoyed before the Fall, or kindling of <hi>Lucifer.</hi> What he might have ſome hopes of; whereas <hi>Lucifer</hi>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:34920:30"/>hath none; becauſe thô he had killed God in him, like <hi>Lucifer,</hi> that is, put out his own Light, yet he was not the Author of the Evil in Nature; had not infected the world, and brought corruption in it; but, on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, the world had inſected him, when he taſted of the Apple, and received into him the Sacrament of the Tree, or Fruit of Good and Evil, as being a mixture of both theſe, and out of which his Body was extracted, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.7. whereby he had that in him which drew him, and made him apt to luſt and long after it. But theſe things are too prolix; and therefore to make at once an end of this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, and reaſſume the Diſcourſe of our Application, I ſay, thus:</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>But if what I did ſpeak of be true, how many are miſtaken, who, doubtleſs, think otherwiſe? And is it not the Duty of them that are in power, both to believe it themſelves, and to uſe the means proper to make others believe it; and to prepare themſelves, and become capable and fit for the Birth of the Spirit? To which end, Is not reading the Bible to be promoted; and therefore learning to read to be by Law enjoined? And ſo ſhould not an Act be made to oblige all People, both Men, Women, and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in the Land, to learn to read; and to read the Bible at home every Sunday at leaſt: and to appoint ſome godly diſcreet Men in each Pariſh, to go from Houſe to Houſe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techizing, and ſeeing whether every one reads, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands what he reads? For why ſhould not <hi>England</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Kingdom of Prieſts? Why ſhould they not hear themſelves God ſpeak to them by that Voice which inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Penmen of Scripture, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. out of Scripture, the Voice that Chriſt's Sheep hear beſt, <hi>John</hi> 10.27. what they cannot hope to do, whil'ſt they run from Church to Church, <hi>ſtealing every one God's words from his Neighbours mouth,</hi> Jer. 23.30. and follow after ſtrangers, <hi>John</hi> 10.5.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:34920:30"/>ſuch as are thoſe that know Chriſt no better than their Shepherds. I am very conſident, that as the Neglect of this is <hi>Prima Mali Labes;</hi> or the Original Cauſe of the Smoke of Popery, <hi>Fumus ab aquilone,</hi> the North is over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.31. and of the preſent darkneſs and ignorance of God in <hi>England</hi> and in <hi>Ireland;</hi> ſo it is the only means to prevent all <hi>Popery,</hi> and to make of <hi>England</hi> a holy Royal Prieſthood, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5, 9 And what if it ſhould follow from hence, that the <hi>top of the Shepherd's Carmel doth wither,</hi> and their <hi>Habitations mourn, Amos</hi> 1.2. and are leſt them deſolate. 'Tis but what muſt come to paſs, if the words of Chriſt be true, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.38. and it will alſo follow that <hi>Zion,</hi> or the true Church, <hi>ſhall bloſſom, and bud again, and take root, and fill with fruit the face of the</hi> Engliſh <hi>world,</hi> Iſa. 27.6. and then their Habitations may become that which they were at the firſt intended for; Houſes for pious Uſes, for Charity, and good Works; to entertain the poor, lame, and decrepit Seamen in: who ſtand more in need of it, and deſerve it far better than the dumb, lazy Shepherds; as keeping the Flock ſafer in its Folds, than thoſe Armies that make the Folds deſolate, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.20.</p>
            <p>But what would become of us? What would at laſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of a Flock without Shepherds? To this I reply, Firſt, When Men are all taught of God, they need no other Teacher: and they may be taught of him, by reading of the Scriptures, as well as I have been, who read no other Book of Divinity but that, and was never taught any Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity in my Life. Secondly, As I grant that all are not taught of God, ſo you grant, I ſuppoſe, that however there will be ſome that ſhall be taught of him; who would be able to teach others, and very ready, becauſe they had it freely, to give it again freely, or to teach without reward, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10 7. What, as the Times go now, the Shepherds cannot well do: for they buy it, pay for it, nay, they give great Rates for it:
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:34920:31"/>the Church of <hi>Samariae</hi> paid dear for an Aſſes head, 2 <hi>King</hi> 6.25. Thirdly, No Kingdom is like a Flock without Shepherd: for it hath always Rulers able to keep good Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, to encourage. Virtue, to puniſh and repreſs Vice, and to compel Men to live within the Bounds of Juſtice, and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> common Honeſty. And this comes nearer to true Right teouſneſs, and to the true Worſhip of God in Spirit, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> when they are permitted to walk after their own Luſts provided they go to Church to mumble, and to hear other mumbling over their Prayers, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.8. For when Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> live Righteouſly, they are fitted thereby for the birth o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Spirit, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.35. and to be met with by it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and by that knowledge of God, as brings them eternal, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alſo temporal Life, and Health, and Felicity, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Deu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 28. <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.29. Whereas when they are ſuffer'd t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> give way to all their Luſts, as they are now in <hi>England</hi> God meets them with nothing elſe than the Smoke that ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth out of the bottomleſs Pit, and, with the Locuſts, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> breeds, whoſe Faces or Appearance are like the Faces o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Men, and whoſe ſhapes are like unto Horſes prepared t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Battel, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.2, 3, 7. that is, with the darkneſs and abominable Armies of old and new <hi>Popery,</hi> and tith Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Wars. The <hi>Huguenots, Waldenſes,</hi> and all the <hi>Eaſter Churches</hi> have vaniſhed in their time, and made room ſo other <hi>Sects.</hi> And ſo will, I am afraid, the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>England,</hi> except they mend, and return to the ancient Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian way; which is their only ſure ground for a laſt in Settlement and Union amongſt themſelves. For the Ax<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is already laid to the Root of their Tree: God hath begun it in <hi>France:</hi> and continues in <hi>Ireland:</hi> and he will finiſh his work in <hi>England,</hi> and other parts of the North, excep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they do prevent him by Repentance. Which God grant is the Prayer, and the main Deſign of the Author in thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Writing.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
